<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A courteous conference with the English Catholikes Romane about the six articles ministred vnto the seminarie priestes, wherein it is apparantly proued by their owne diuinitie, and the principles of their owne religion, that the Pope cannot depose her Maiestie, or release her subiectes of their alleageance vnto her. And finally, that the bull of Pius Quiutus [sic] pronounced against her Maiestie is of no force eyther in lawe or conscience, all Catholicke scruples to the contrarie beeing throughly and perfectly cleared and resolued, and many memoriall matters exactly discussed, which haue not beene handled by man heeretofore. Written by Iohn Bishop a recusant papist.</title>
            <author>Bishop, John, d. 1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3092</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102284</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838074</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838074</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2432</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16170)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2432)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 452:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A courteous conference with the English Catholikes Romane about the six articles ministred vnto the seminarie priestes, wherein it is apparantly proued by their owne diuinitie, and the principles of their owne religion, that the Pope cannot depose her Maiestie, or release her subiectes of their alleageance vnto her. And finally, that the bull of Pius Quiutus [sic] pronounced against her Maiestie is of no force eyther in lawe or conscience, all Catholicke scruples to the contrarie beeing throughly and perfectly cleared and resolued, and many memoriall matters exactly discussed, which haue not beene handled by man heeretofore. Written by Iohn Bishop a recusant papist.</title>
                  <author>Bishop, John, d. 1613.</author>
                  <author>Frewen, John, 1558-1628.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by R. Bradock] for Robert Dexter dwelling in Paules Church-yard ar the signe of the Brasen Serpent,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Edited by John Frewen.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A courteous conference with the English Catholickes Romaine.</note>
                  <note>Variant: title has "Euglish".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church. --  Pope (1566-1572 : Pius V). --  Regnans in excelsis.</term>
               <term>Popes --  Temporal power --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2432:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2432:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A COVRTEOVS CONFERENCE <hi>with the Engliſh Catholickes Romane, about</hi> the ſix Articles miniſtred vnto the Seminarie prieſtes, <hi>wherein it is apparantly proued by their owne diuinitie, and the principles of their owne religion, that the Pope cannot depoſe</hi> her Maieſtie, or releaſe her ſubiectes of their alleageance vnto her. And finally, that the Bull of <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> pronounced againſt her Maieſtie is of no force ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in lawe or conſcience, all Catholicke ſcruples to the contrarie beeing throughly and perfectly cleared and reſolued, and many memoriall matters exactly diſcuſſed, which haue not beene handled by any man heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore. <hi>Written by</hi> Iohn Biſhop <hi>a recuſant papiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Dexter, featuring a hand pointing to a star (McKerrow 260)</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>DEVS IMPERAT ASTRIS</q>
               </head>
               <p>R D</p>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Imprinted for Robert Dexter dwelling in</hi> Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the <hi>Braſen Serpent.</hi> 1598.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2432:2"/>
            <head>The Six propoſitions handled in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at the Pope and all the Biſhoppes and prieſtes are ſubiect by the we of God vnto the temperall magiſtrate, in whoſe Realme and Dominions they doe dwell.</item>
               <item>2 That they cannot depriue Chriſtian princes of their principalities.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> That the Pope cannot looſe ſubiectes of their natural faith and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence vnto their prince.</item>
               <item>4 That it is no determination of faith, that the Pope may depoſe princes.</item>
               <item>5 That the Canon made at the counſell of <hi>Laterane,</hi> touching the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of princes (the which hath bredde the greateſt ſcruple in the conſciences of our Catholickes Romane) neither is, nor euer was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e within this land.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> That the ſentence pronounced againſt her Maieſtie, was neither lawfully, nor orderly done, according vnto the <hi>Laterane</hi> Canon.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:2432:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Booke (Chriſtian Reader) was written by one <hi>Iohn Biſhop</hi> a recuſant papiſt, what ſufficient reaſon there is (notwithſtanding) to commit it to the preſſe, and from thence to the open veiw of all men, in the diligent peruſing, &amp; conſideration ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thou maiſt plainely perceiue and vnderſtand. It is a booke which (in the iudgement of many godly and learned men) is very neceſſary to come abroad, neither hath anie obiection bene made againſt the publiſhing of the ſame, but onely this, that it is to be feared, it will be a meanes to bring the papiſtes into more fauour, as diſcouering them to be nothing ſuch dangerous enemies to the ſtate, as of the greateſt part they are reputed: but ſurely I ſee no cauſe to ſtand in feare of any ſuch effect, but rather to reſt fully reſolued vpon the contrarie, that for aſmuch as, howſoeuer ſome one of them being aſtoniſhed with the light of Gods trueth, and looking backe to the former times, ſheweth himſelf nothing ſo abſurd as other, yet ſeeing the profeſſed doctrine of their Church is otherwiſe, and the continuall practiſe of the Pope, &amp; all his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes is directly to the contrarie, by murders, treaſons, and rebellions, and by the inuaſions &amp; open force of cruell enemies ſeeking the vtter deſtruction of the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie (whom God manie yeares yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue) and of all others that profeſſe in trueth the glorious Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt: accounting the Popes Bulles a ſufficient warrant for the ouerturning of Gods ordinances, and his pardons, a ſtrong bulwarke againſt the wrath of God, againſt hell &amp; condemnation. Theſe things I ſay conſidered, I ſee no reaſon to feare anie encreaſe of their fauour and credit by this meanes, but rather to hope (as there is iuſt cauſe to deſire) the encreaſe of their diſcredit, and more ſtraiter lawes for the reſtraining of them. The magiſtrate hath had too much experience, that howſoeuer the iudgements of ſome of the beſt learned among the papiſtes may peraduenture agree with the author of this booke, yet the profeſſion &amp; practiſe of them all, both learned &amp; vnlearned is farre otherwiſe, as by open and outragious attempts there wants no good will in them to teſtifie more plainely vnto the whole worlde, if the day were once come they haue ſo long looked for, &amp; if they ſaw any likelihood of preuailing, but as the Lord for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake hath hitherto defeyted their purpoſes, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned their miſchieuous imaginations to their owne cunfuſion, ſo I nothing doubt, but he will continue for vs a braſen wall of defence from time to time heereafter euen vntill the ſecond comming of his ſonne in the cloudes.</p>
            <p>Whether the author would himſelfe haue publiſhed this booke, it is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that at the writing hereof he was ſo determined, it is very probable by that part of his preface which is come to our hands, where he beginneth thus.
<pb facs="tcp:2432:3"/> 
               <hi>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſaw two or three years paſt many ſeminary prieſts:</hi> that which next enſued after theſe words was rent off and ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be found, but on the other ſide of the paper it followeth thus. <hi>And whiles I, following</hi> Horace <hi>his counſaile</hi> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> premitur in annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>did let this treatiſe lie by me in ſeaſoning, that it might at length paſſe abroad perfect, fully refuting all obiections of moment which old ſhops had ſhapened, or new forges had framed, &amp;c.</hi> By this I ſay it appeareth that at the time of the writing therof, he was fully determined to imprint this booke, but afterwards it ſhould ſee me his mind was altred, perſwading himſelfe that the publiſhing would greatly tend to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence &amp; diſquieting of his Catholick brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For how is it poſſible, that they ſhould take it patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to ſee one of their owne profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo eagerly fight againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the foile with their owne weapons, &amp; by the exprſſe teſtimony alſo of the holy ſcriptures, &amp; by ſo many approued authorities &amp; examples, diſcouering to the world, the tyranny, the malicious, the proud &amp; arrogant practiſes of their holy father. Surely ſo far would they haue bene from taking it in good part at his hand whiles he was aliue, that I am fully perſwaded, they neither can, nor will, with hold their tongues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exclaiming againſt him now he is dead, either accounting him to be an Apoſtata, or els making themſelues bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue that this worke is falſey fathered vpon him. But to put them out of doubt both of the one, &amp; the other. That he was no backſlider fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but vnto his dying day continued a recuſant papiſt, it is ſo wel knowen at Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> where he was borne &amp; often co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſant, &amp; at <hi>London</hi> where he ſpent a great part of his time, as alſo in all the country neare vnto Battel, as that there nedeth not any further teſtimony. And that he was in very truth the author of this booke, &amp; of euery part therof, is manifeſtly, to be proued by his owne hand writing, ſo well knowen at Battel &amp; in the cuntry therabouts &amp; alſo of many in <hi>London,</hi> as that there is no neede to feare the clearing alſo of this ſcruple. Let any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that knoweth his hand, &amp; is deſirous to be reſolued of the trueth, repaire to <hi>Northhiham</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> &amp; at the houſe of <hi>George Biſhop</hi> brother to the deceaſed author, he ſhal at his pleaſure haue a ſight of the ſame. To conclude, this alſo wiſely &amp; diligently is the reader to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that although he write very directly againſt the Pope &amp; popery, yet in many reſpects doth he ſhew himſelf a papiſt, as in following of corrupt tranſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, in the places of ſcripture which he alledgeth, &amp; in miſapplying many of them, contrary to the true ſenſe &amp; meaning of the holy Ghoſt, wherein al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome warni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g is giuen by a few marginall notes added of purpoſe and ſigned wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this letter, yet cannot the godly reader for all that be too wearie and circumſpect in the particular conſideration of the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <p>Pag. 2. for euery, read (euery). Pag. 3. for iu?, read ni? Pa. 4. for Iunius, read. Fumus Pag 7. for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2432:3"/>
            <head>A COVRTEOVS <hi>conference with the Engliſh Catholicks</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane about the ſix Articles miniſtred vnto the <hi>Seminarie prieſtes, wherein it is apparantly proued by their</hi> owne diuinitie and the principles of their owne religi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n that the Pope cannot depoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her Maieſty or relea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e her ſubiects of their Allegiance vnto her.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow then to proue my firſt propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition that the Pope and all the Biſhoppes and Prieſtes are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect by the law of God vnto the temporall magiſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te,<note place="margin">All per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the temporal magiſtrat.</note> in whoſe realme and dominions they doe dwell, thus I prooue, <hi>Salomon. Prou.</hi> 24. ſaith my ſonne feare the Lord and King, and intermeddle not or be not among detractors, for their diſtruction wil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe ſodainly and who knoweth the ruine of them both. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle in his writing to the Romaines thus exhorteth or rather commandeth them <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher power for there is noe power but from God: but thoſe which are, were ordained by God &amp;c. So then he that reſiſteth the power reſiſteth the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God but they which doe reſiſt do get themſelues da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation: for princes be no feare of good worke but of il, but wilt thou not feare the power? doe well and then ſhalt thou haue praiſe thereby, for he is the miniſter of God vnto thee to good; but if thou haue done ill, then feare for he beareth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2432:4"/> not the ſword without cauſe; he is the miniſter of God, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenger in wrath to him that doth ill. And therfore ye muſt needes be ſubiect, not onely for wrath but alſo for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, for therefore doe yea alſo pay tribute, for they are the miniſters of God ſeruing for this very purpoſe. Alſo in his epiſtle to <hi>Titus Cap. 3.</hi> he writes: warne them to be ſubiect to principalities &amp; powers, to obey their commandements. Moreouer <hi>S. Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> from whom the Pope clameth his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thus writeth in his firſt vniuerſall epiſtle <hi>Cap. 2.</hi> Be ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ub ect to euery humain creature for the Lord, whether it be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt excellent or vnto the preſidents, as ſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him, to the reuenge of euil deedes, but to the praiſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good becauſe ſo is the will of God, that ye doing well, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay make m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re the ignorance of the vnſkilfull as free men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> as men that haue libertie for a cloake of naughtineſſe, but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the bondmen of God, and anone after, feare God and honour the King. Ye do ſee how the old and new law doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the ſupreeme authoritie of princes, ouer all perſons borne or abiding within their dominions. <hi>Paul</hi> vſing this v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall euery, excepting none, and <hi>Salomon</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite, in this place equall vnto an vniuerſall. And <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> doe in expreſſe wordes giue vnto him the ſupreeme Emp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re of adminiſtring iuſtice in puniſhing the wicked &amp; rewarding the good; and that he is ſo the Apoſtle doth proue by that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll men pay him tribute, the which alſo he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to be paide, and alſo chargeth all men to be obedient vnto him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not for feare onely, leſt otherwiſe the prince would make them ſmart, but alſo for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ſake, becauſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are in duety bound ſo to do, for that God had ordained them to be his lieuetenants in gouernement. And therefore if they were not obedient vnto them, they muſt needs be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted &amp; reputed for rebels vnto God, that would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept him for their ſoueraigne whom God had ſet ouer them. And <hi>Peter</hi> to ſuppres the carnal cogitation of the <hi>Iewes</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2432:4"/> vnto whom he wrot that thought that the meſſias had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franchiſed them, by his rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption from al ſubiection to man &amp; alſo to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the proud opinion of the clergy that ſhould come after, who would clame exemption from earthly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, becauſe they were appointed &amp; ordained diſpenſers of the miſteries of the Meſſias: he flatly affirmeth the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of ſuch libertie to be nothing elſe put a plaine pretence &amp; cloake for their naughtineſſe: For he would they ſhoulde reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that although they were deliuered by Chriſt from the bondage &amp; tiranny of ſin, death &amp; the Deuill, yet they remained ſtill his &amp; his fathers bondmen, &amp; therfore ought duetifully to obey ſtill the ciuill magiſtrats, whom God hath placed in his owne throne, his king &amp; his lieuetenant ouer them. And therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> in the place afore alleadged,<note place="margin">An appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in ſecular cauſes cannot be made to the Pope.</note> ioyneth them together ſaying: feare God and the King. God principally (ſaith <hi>Lyra</hi> writing on that place) and ſecundari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the King who is his Vicar in temporall things. This being ſo, I cannot chuſe but much maruaile at that ſaying in <hi>Cap. Licet de ſor. comp.</hi> that an appellation may be made from all princes temporall. Yea &amp; ſuch as do acknowledge no ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour in temporalities, when none other can be had, and the matter is of ſom weight. For if as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie that there is no man aboue the Emperour, <hi>et quem ſoli Deo ſubiicio</hi> and whome I make vnder none but God, &amp; in annother place of the ſame Apologie he ſaith of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours of Rome, <hi>in Dei ſolius potestate ſunt, a quo ſunt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundi, poſt quem primi ante omnes, et ſuper omnes deos, quid in? cum ſuper omnes homines,</hi> they are vnder God only, vnto whom they are ſeconde after whom they are firſt, before all men, and aboue all gods, and why not? ſeeing they are aboue all men. And againe if it be true that the graue and learned light of our Lawiers <hi>Bracton,</hi> that liued almoſt foure hundreth yeares agoe, in the raigne of <hi>Henry</hi> the thirde, doth affirme in the beginning of his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2432:5"/> booke, that a King cannot be a King, if he haue any ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in thoſe things that doe appertaine vnto his crowne and kingdome, and may not haue in his kingdome any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall much leſſe any ſuperiour eſpecially in adminiſtration of iuſtice, that it may be ſaide of him: Great is our Lorde &amp; greate is his power &amp;c. And that he doth aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irme him to be the vicar of God on earth;<note place="margin">This place Pſal. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od.</note> I can not ſee by what right or reaſon, an appellation in a ſecular cauſe can be made from an Emperour, King or any ſupreame temporall magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate vnto the Pope ſeeing he is not theire ſuperiour in temporalities. For all the worlde knoweth that an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation can not be made but from an inferiour iudge, vnto an higher, and alſo his ſuperiour in that kinde of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction. But much more am I amaſed at that impudent aſſertion <hi>Cap. tibi domino. 63. D.</hi> and inſerted by <hi>Iunius</hi> into his <hi>armilla aurea</hi> in the title of <hi>Papa, Omnis poteſtas iurat fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitatem Papae, et obedientiam, recognoſcens ab eo omne quod hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not yet n ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> 
               <hi>Et ſi aliquando aliquis imperator donabit Eccleſiae vt de Conſtantine dicitur, non fuit donatio ſed restitutio.</hi> Euerye power doth ſweate feaulty and obedience vnto the Pope acknowledgeing from him all that he hath. And if at any time ſome Emperour gaue vnto the Church as is reported of Conſtantine it was no giuing but a reſtoring: For this is ſo repugnant vnto the holy ſcriptures and the common opinion of all diuines both ancient and moderne that moſt of our Catholickes Romains I thinke will be ſoe farre from defending it, that they namely, the vnlearned ſort will as ſoone as euer they reade it cry out at me, as a moſt ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe lyer for alleaging of ſoe ſhamefull a ſentence. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though as I ſaide our Catholique Romane will not perhaps affirme that, <hi>Papae eſt terra &amp; plenitudo eius, orbis terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vniuerſi qui habitant in ea,</hi> the earth is the Popes and the fulneſſe thereof, the orbe of the earthes and all that dwell therein.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2432:5"/>
            <p>Yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doe nothing doubt but diuers of them doe holde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taught by their ſchoolemaſter <hi>Pighius</hi> and other that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit <hi>Peter</hi> and the Apoſtles were ſubiect vnto the Emperors and vnder other heathen ſtates vnder whom they were borne and abode, yet alter that the Emperours and Kinges of the earth became Chriſtians and did voluntarily put their necks vnder the yoke of Chriſt,<note place="margin">The pops nor bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops haue any ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> they ſtraightway became <hi>ipſo facto</hi> ſubiect vnto the Pope Chriſt his Lieuetenant generall in earth: according to the propheſie of <hi>Eſay. Cap. 60.</hi> the nation and kingdome that will not ſerue thee <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhall periſh: but how truely let vs conſider. For firſt that the ſenſe of this ſaying of the prophet is not ſuch as <hi>Pighius</hi> ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth but rather this,<note place="margin">A place of Eſay an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> that euerie nation that will not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Chriſt for their God, Lord and Sauiour, and be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient vnto his precepts and ordinances ſhall periſh, I doe thinke is ſo apparant that it needeth no proofe and ſpoken onely of his ſpirituall kingdome on the earth which his father gaue vnto him as Meſſias as it is written in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Pſalme. Thou art my ſonne this day did I beget thee, aske of mee and I will giue thee the nations for thine inheritance, and the boundes of the earth for thy poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and then as alſo in this place of <hi>Eſay</hi> he commaundeth the kinges to ſerue him in feare, and to accept him for their prince, and embrace his diſcipline and doctrine or elſe they ſhould periſh. Now ſeeing this was a newe kingdome, and inheritance giuen him by his father latelie, it cannot be vnderſtoode of the bodily and earthly kingdome, for he as God was poſſeſſed of that before, and from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; according to that ſaying of <hi>Dauid.</hi> The earth is the Lordes and the fulneſſe thereof, the orbe of the earth and all that dwell therein. But of his newe and newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored kingdome conſiſting of beleeuing ſoules, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the kingdom of heauen, whereof hee thus ſpeaketh, vnto his Apoſtles and meſſengers after his reſurrection: all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2432:6"/> power is giuen me in heauen and in earth, wherefore goe ye and proclame, publiſh and make knowen vnto nations, how my father hath giuen me the Empyre of the whole earth, and that thoſe which ſhal refuſe to weare my badge of baptiſme, and to obſerue and keepe my lawes &amp; ordinances while they liue on earth, ſhall after death be ſhut out of heauen &amp; bliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full paradiſe. And ſo haue all both olde and late writers that euer I ſaw interpreted this place, and not of any earthly and ſeruile ſubiection, as <hi>Hierome,</hi> the nations and kings that will not ſerue the Church in a good and profitable bondage or ſeruice that they may be transferred into the Apoſtolicall dignitie: as <hi>Haimo</hi> ſhall ſerue thee by faith and good works: As <hi>Leo de Caſtro,</hi> who interpreteth that by this place of the Goſpell: He that will beleeue and be baptiſed ſhalbe ſaued; but he that will not beleeue ſhal be condemned. And as <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerius</hi> an other learned Spaniſh Fryer, that thoſe which will not come into and continue in the true Church of Chriſt ſhall perich: And this to be the true meaning of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet doth the next ſentence before plainely conuince. Thy gates ſhall ſtand open continually, day and night ſhall they not be ſhut, that the ſtrength of the nations or gentiles may be brought vnto thee, and the kinges of them led vnto thee for the nation, &amp;c. Neyther is <hi>Pighius</hi> his cauſe any thing better aduanced by an authority of <hi>Nazianzene</hi> borrowed out of <hi>Gratian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A place of Nazianze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> but afterward alledged by <hi>Saunders</hi> and <hi>Allen</hi> more according to the trueth of the text which they doe ſet downe in theſe wordes. What will you not be content that I doe ſpeake my minde freely: for the lawe of Chriſt doth ſubiect you to my power, and vnto my barre: for we alſo haue an empyre, yea &amp; I doe ſay more a more excellent and perfect then yours: vnleſſe it be meete that the ſpirit do ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it ſelfe to the fleſh, and that heauenly thinges giue place to earthly. For who is ſo blinde that cannot ſee that <hi>Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zene</hi> doth in this ſpeach chalenge none other then a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2432:6"/> gouernment, ſuch as our Biſhops haue heere ouer their dioceſſes, and prieſtes ouer their pariſhes a charge of ſoules, and therefore becauſe it hath the care and ordering of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and heauenly things, he doth affirme it to be more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent &amp; perfect then the Empyre of kings who do rule ouer the bodies and goods of men: So that no wordes can more manifeſtly depriue the Pope and prieſtes of all earthly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre and commaund in temporall thinges then theſe doe which doe affirme them to belong to the ciuill magiſtrate, their office being only occupied in ſauing of ſoules, by ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall meanes, and onely in matters ſpirituall &amp; heauenly, as preaching, praying, adminiſtration of the ſacraments, and ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall diſcipline, and ſuch like appropriated to prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode; and that this was his meaning &amp; mind it is apparant by the wordes which he vſeth before to the Citizens of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zanſe</hi> in the which he doth acknowledge himſelfe, and all the clergie ſubiect vnto the ſecular ſoueraigne ſaying thus. But among other lawes of our doctrine, we haue alſo this moſt laudable law inacted, by the which as bondmen are comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to obey &amp; to be obedient vnto their maſters, &amp; wiues vnto their husbands, and the Church vnto Chriſt &amp; diſciples and ſchollers to their ſchoolemaſters and paſtors; ſo are we alſo preſcribed to obey the ſuperexcellent powers, not only for wrath but alſo for conſcience, as we that are bounde to payment of tribute. Neyther let vs ſo behaue our ſelues, that we for our wickednes and lewde factes, doe deadly hate the lawe and looke for the reuenging ſword, but rather ſo leade our liues that we may get praiſe of the power and magiſtrate: And then after he hath very eloquently ſhewed by many ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes that they ought not to blame the harmleſſe of the ſword, but to impute the ſmart thereof vnto their owne faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe; he leaueth as he ſaith the ſubiectes and turneth his ſpeach vnto the Emperour and the gouernours, for ye muſt vnderſtand that this oration was pronounced in the preſence
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2432:7"/> of the people of <hi>Nazanſe,</hi> trembling for feare of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours great diſpleaſure and alſo of the angry Emperour and his officers, leaſt he ſhould be thought (theſe are his words) to deale altogether partially eyther not ſeeming to haue the like care ouer them to whome he ought more hoofully to looke vnto, as they that could do moſt either harme or good, as he had of the other inferiour ſorte: or elſe to haue loſt through feare or ſhame the freedom that he had from Chriſt not daring to admoniſh them of their duetie, becauſe of their great dignity and power. And then he vſeth the words alleadged by our aduerſaries; what wil ye not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent &amp;c. But I doe not doubt but your maieſtie wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l take this my free ſpeaking in good part, as a holy ſheepe of my holy flocke, and a weaneling of the great ſheepeheard. And then he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth very effectuall reaſons to moue him to mercy, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally falleth to pitifull obteſtations, by his owne hoary head, his immaculate prieſthood which the Angels &amp;c. by Chriſt his bitter paſſion, &amp;c. in moſt ſuppliant ſort, without any one word that any whit ſauoureth or ſoundeth of authority, power or commaund, wiſely and godly teaching the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes duetifull obedience, and the Emperour and his offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers mercy and moderation in gouernment. Furthermore the better to boult out the trueth, in the controuerſy I thinke it will not be amiſſe to ſearch out, whether in the old lawe the high prieſt who was a type and figure of Chriſt, and head of all the prieſtes, and had the ſupreme miniſtration of the myſteries of God,<note place="margin">The high prieſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</note> and in whoſe name of <hi>Pontifex,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſucceeded, was ſubiect vnto the ciuill magiſtrate or noe. And that he was is plainely proued in the <hi>2. Cap.</hi> of <hi>3. Kings</hi> where <hi>Salomon</hi> depoſeth <hi>Abiather</hi> the high prieſt, of his office, and confirmeth him into <hi>Anathotb</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had gone about to make <hi>Adoniah</hi> King, and alſo told him that he had deſerued to die; but he would not put him to death, becauſe he had borne the Arke of the Lord
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2432:7"/> God, before his father <hi>Dauid,</hi> and had beene a continuall partaker of all his fathers troubles. Then if <hi>Salomon</hi> might lawfully execute the high prieſt for treaſon there is no doubt but that the high prieſtes were ſubiect vnto the kinges, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſoueraignes.</p>
            <p>But although I will paſſe ouer in ſilence, the putting to death of the high prieſt <hi>Achimelech</hi> and <hi>Azarias</hi> by <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ioas</hi> becauſe they will cauill they were tyrannicall, yer I will ſtay a little vpon the ſuppliant ſpeach of <hi>Achimelech</hi> becauſe it argueth ſubiection in the ſpeaker. <hi>Saul</hi> vpon the occaſion of <hi>Doeg</hi> ſent for <hi>Achimelech</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Achitob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 22. 19. Cap.</note> &amp; all the hole howſe of his father being prieſtes which were in <hi>Nob,</hi> who came euery man vnto the king, and <hi>Saul</hi> ſaide: Liſten thou ſonne of <hi>Achitob:</hi> who anſwered I am heere my Lord. And <hi>Saul</hi> ſaide why haſt thou and the ſonne of <hi>Iſhai</hi> conſpired againſt me: and haſt giuen him being a trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour (and ſo continuing to this day) bread and a ſword, and haſt asked counſaile of God for him, that he might riſe vp againſt me? And <hi>Achimelech</hi> anſwering the king thus ſpake? Let this crime be farre from me, neyther let the king ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any ſuch thing againſt his bondman, nor of any man of the whole howſe of my father: For thy bondman knew nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leſſe nor much of this matter, &amp;c. Doth there not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in theſe wordes almoſt a ſeruile ſubiection of the high prieſtes vnto the king? for by what baſer terme can he call himſelfe then his bondman? or by what higher and more ſoueraigne name could he ſpeake vnto the king then calling him his Lord? a word that doth ſignifie the prince to haue his ſubiectes in ſuch ſeruilitie: that <hi>Octauian</hi> the Emperour that did accept the names of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> or diuine, of father of his country &amp;c. to haue his name ſworne by and his images ſacrificed vnto as a God:<note place="margin">19 Cap. 2. Crome.</note> Yet wold neuer admit as <hi>Suetonius</hi> and <hi>Dion</hi> doe affirme the title of Lord but abhorred it as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochfull, although now time and cuſtome haue mollified
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2432:8"/> the worde. But that the high prieſt had nothing to din mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſtate, we haue it ſet downe in flat wordes in the 19. of the ſecond <hi>Paralip,</hi> or the <hi>Chronicles</hi> where this we doe reade. But <hi>Amarias</hi> the prieſt and your high prieſt ſhall be preſident or chiefe in thoſe thinges which doe appertaine to God, but <hi>Zebadias</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iſhmaell</hi> who is captaine of the houſe of <hi>Iuda,</hi> ſhall be ouer thoſe workes which doe belong vnto the king. But now that we haue ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the ſubiection of the high prieſt of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> let vs come to Chriſt himſelfe by pretence of being whoſe vicar and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie in earth the Pope claimeth this prowde prerogatiue of pearching ouer princes,<note place="margin">Chriſt no earthlie ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g.</note> and diſcuſſe whether that he, as Chriſt and Meſſias, (for I thinke the Pope doth not chalenge to be Gods but Chriſtes vicar,) was an earthly Monarch or noe; that he was none, it is apparantly prooued, by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to giue iudgement on a woman accuſed of adulterie,<note place="margin">Iohn. 8.</note> and alſo by denying himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe to bee a competent iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two brothers, that contended about an inheritance. And finally in that he confeſſed vnto <hi>Pilate</hi> in expreſſe words that his kingdome was not of this world.<note place="margin">Iohn. 18.</note> As for the paying of foure drachmes for himſelfe &amp; <hi>Peter</hi> at <hi>Capernaum,</hi> I thinke with <hi>Theophylactus</hi> and ſome other that it was for the halfe ſycle (which is two drachmes) due vnto the Lord for euerie man that was twentie yeares of age, as we reade in <hi>Exodus</hi> rather then for tribute due to the Emperour, becauſe mee thinketh it doth better agree with Chriſtes interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to <hi>Peter,</hi> what thinkeſt thou <hi>Peter,</hi> of whome doe the kinges of the earth take tribute, of their owne children or of ſtrangers, and he ſayde of ſtrangers: Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſayde vnto him then are the children free. As though he ſhoulde haue ſayde.<note place="margin">This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n is vtterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the meaning and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of Chriſt, as the godly reader, doth well vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note> If Kinges children doe not pay tribute to their fathers, neyther ought I to pay vnto God any, becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e I am his ſonne: But if any man will contend that hee affirmed that he ought to pay no tribute to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2432:8"/> Emperour, becauſe he was the ſonne of the ſupreme Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour God Almightie, I will not greatly ſtriue with him, but I will in noe wiſe graunt <hi>Felicius</hi> that he claimes to be diſcharged, by right of any earthlie Empyre that he poſſeſſed as Chriſt; for that by no meanes can be gathered out of the text, yea what ſay you that that famous fryer <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicus Soto</hi> doth holde in learned worke <hi>de Iustit. &amp; Iure,</hi> that the kingdome of Chriſt was meere ſpirituall, and writeth that he had proued it at large in his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries vppon <hi>Mathew.</hi> Moreouer the matter is ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that <hi>Pighius</hi> himſelfe is forced to confeſſe that Chriſt his kingdome was onely ſpirituall, and yet he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to him whome he woulde haue to be his deputie, temporall ſuperioritie ouer all Chriſtian princes in that hee is Chriſt his Lieuetenant, with as greate abſurdidie as if a man ſhoulde denie that the Archbiſhoppe of <hi>Canterburie</hi> can heare and determine of felonies, and yet holde that his officiall may, or depriue the Conſtable of authoritie to enter forciblie into any mans houſe, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then in caſes of treaſon and felonie, and yet graunt it to the Conſtables deputie, or to ſay that hir Maieſtie can not put in or out at hir pleaſure, anie ſouldiours into hir towne of <hi>Barwicke,</hi> and yet maintaine that hir Lieuetenaunt of the Towne may doe it. And ſee I pray you how he anſwereth this obiection out of the Goſpell, as my father ſent me ſo I ſende you. Whereas they ſay that Chriſt came not to exerciſe authoritie and empyre ouer Monarches, Kinges and princes, but as he was ſente by the father,<note place="margin">Chriſt gaue no temporal power to Biſhops nor Pope</note> ſoe he doth witneſſe that the Apoſtles were ſent by him, neyther therefore had they authoritie ouer kinges and princes they gather not aright, for that word (as) doth not import a likenes in all points betweene them whih were ſent, Chiſt and his Apoſtles: but doth ſhew the ſenders or the authoritie of the ſenders: As if he had ſaide, my
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2432:9"/> father ſent me but I ſend you, otherwiſe Chriſt was ſent by his father to redeeme mankind by his death, but not ſo ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to that end were the Apoſtles ſent by Chriſt, but for this purpoſe, that they ſhoulde out of all nations gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his kingdom in the which all men ſhould be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his benefits: vnto the which kingdom yet he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had preſcribed lawes, and had ordained <hi>Peter</hi> to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour thereof.<note place="margin">Yet had Peter no more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority then the reſt of the Apoſtles.</note> I deny not but that the ſending of Chriſt did in ſome pointes ſurmount the ſending of the Apoſtles, but that Chriſt ſent forth his Apoſtles with a larger commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and power, then his father had giuen him, that no man I thinke will lightly grant <hi>Pighius,</hi> that knoweth that rule of the Canon Law, yea and I doe thinke of all lawes: <hi>Nemo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt pius iuris conferre in alium quam ſibi competere dignoſcatur.</hi> (No man can giue more right vnto another, then may be knowen is in himſelfe, &amp; the ſaying of Chriſt, that the ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler is not aboue his ſchoolemaſter, nor the bondman aboue his Lord; but it is enough for the ſcholler to be as his maſter is, and the bondman as his Lord. And <hi>Iohn. 13.</hi> Verily verily I ſay vnto you, the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is not greater then his maſter, neither the Apoſtle nor legate or meſſenger greater then him that ſent him. And with what authority he ſent them, it appeareth by the words that immediatly follow: when he had ſaid theſe wordes, he blew vpon them and ſaid vnto them, receiue the holy ghoſt: whoſe ſins ye ſhall remit they are remitted, and whoſe ſins ye ſhall retaine, they are retained: and can any man call this power an earthly empyre? And bycauſe <hi>Pighius</hi> ſaith that Chriſt had ordained <hi>Peter</hi> gouernour of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, I pray let vs conſider what power he gaue vnto him at the time of his inſtitution or inauguration, his wordes be theſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note> I will giue vnto thee the keyes of the kingdome of heauen, and whatſoeuer thou ſhalt binde vpon the earth ſhall alſo be bound in heauen, and whatſoeuer thou ſhalt looſe vpon the earth ſhall be alſo looſed in heauen, yee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2432:9"/> apparantly ſee that Chriſt gaue vnto <hi>Peter</hi> not the keyes of the earthly kingdome or Empire to aduaunce and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Princes, but of the Kingdome of heauen to let in or ſhutte out from heauen, neither had hee a ſworde or Scepter giuen him as enſigne of a King, but a key a token of a porter. So that except the Pope can ſhewe annother Chapter then that which was giuen to <hi>Peter</hi> he will want wordes to carrie away a terrene mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. But although <hi>Pighius</hi> doe grant Chriſte his kingdome to be ſpiriuall, yet <hi>Feliſius</hi> in his booke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the tenne commaundements,<note place="margin">Feliſius obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Chriſts kingdom anſwered.</note> on the Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment honour thy father and thy mother, will not yeelde thereunto; but endeauoureth to proue his ſecular power and monarchy by his practiſe, in deciding all kinde of cauſes as of life and death when he badde <hi>Peter</hi> put vp his ſworde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of criminall when he willed the woman taken in adultery to be gone: and of ciuill when he determined the controuerſi be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Phariſies</hi> &amp; the <hi>Herodians,</hi> whether the <hi>Iewes</hi> ought to pay tribute vnto the Emperours of Rome or noe. Doubtleſſe if <hi>Feliſius</hi> were not accounted for a great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man among the Catholickes Romaine I would not vouchſafe to ſhape theſe obiections an anſweare, they are ſoe friuolous. For who ſeeth not that Chriſt his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Peter</hi> to put vp his ſworde doth no more proue that Chriſt had authoritie of publique Iuſtice, then the bidding of any ſimple gentleman in the Citty of London that his man put vp his ſword which he had drawen in a fray againſt his enemy, will conuince him to be a Iuſtice of the peace of the ſame Citty, But that Chriſt ſaide vnto the woman ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in adultery that ſhe might begonne her way, for ſeeing noe man had conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned hir neyther would he: He doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare that he had noe authoritie to condemne or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine hir, but that ſhe might be gone for any thing he had to ſay or deale with hir. Now for the matter of paying
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2432:10"/> tribute it was not brought before him as a competent Iudge by parties ſueing and ſued by proceſſe awarded, or vppon diſtreſſe taken, but onely moued vnto him as a ſkilful Doctor and learned diuine to be determined, as a doubt betweene the two ſectes of the <hi>Phariſies</hi> and the <hi>Herodians;</hi> As if a Proteſtant and Catholicke ſhould priuately come to Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or <hi>Feliſius</hi> to know his opinion whether the Pope may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Chriſtian Princes or noe, but in very deede they came not to Chriſt to be reſolued of the doubt but onely to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trappe him and to ſee if happely they could bring him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of treaſon; by denying the paiment of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute vnto the Emperour, and ſo procure his death by the Romaine preſident, as ſeditious; And therefore he aſked them why they tempted him, and willed them to ſhew him a peny, and then he demaunded of them whoſe image was ſtamped on the peece, and they anſwered the Emperours; then ſaide he, giue the Emperour that which is his, and ſo likwiſe ynto god that which is gods: a very obſcure ſentence giuen by a iudge in a ſute: but a wiſe and wittie anſwere for ſuch falſe traterous Interrogants. And with the like tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſles doth the ſame <hi>Feliſius</hi> alſo trouble vs, when he goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to proue the exemption of the clergy fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> free ſubiection of ſecular princes becauſe <hi>Melchiſdech</hi> was both a king and a prieſt, &amp; ſo likewiſe Moſes a prieſt &amp; ſupreme gouernor of the <hi>Iſeralites:</hi> And finally <hi>Hely</hi> was both high prieſt, and alſo ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Prince or iudge of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> For if <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> were both a King and a Prieſt what is that to the controuerſie that we haue now in hand, whether that Prieſtes be ſubiect vnto the temporall Prince: (but perhaps it touched the matter if we had diſputed whether that a Biſhop may be alſo a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Prince,<note place="margin">See Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtella.</note> As for a King to be a Prieſt was an vſual thing in many countries among the heathen: Yea all the Romaine Kings had the chiefe charge of the ſacrifices, temples and worſhippe of the gods, and therefore when the Kinges
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2432:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> were expelled they ordained a prieſt whom they called the ſacrificing King, who ſhould execute thoſe publicke ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices which did of right belong vnto the Kings function, but for hatred of their kings made him ſubiect vnto the chiefe Prieſt or <hi>Pontifiex Maximus:</hi> the which office of <hi>Pontifiex Maximus</hi> all the heathen Romaine Emperours continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had.<note place="margin">See Dion. &amp;c.</note> But that <hi>Moſes</hi> was both the ciuill magiſtrate and alſo a prieſt it maketh very much againſt himſelfe, for although we doe grant that <hi>Moſes</hi> was a Prieſt, yet it is moſt manifeſt that he was not high Prieſt, but his brother <hi>Aaron</hi> whome yet to be ſubiect vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> all men ſeene in the ſacred ſcriptures do knowe, ſo that nothing can make more for the ſuperioritie of the ciuill magiſtrate then this example that <hi>Aaron</hi> being high Prieſt and head and chiefe of all Prieſtes, was yet ſubiect to <hi>Moſes</hi> an ordinary Prieſt,<note place="margin">Moſes was a prophet and not a prieſt.</note> becauſe he had the ſoueraigntie temporall. Likewiſe what is it to the purpoſe if that <hi>Hely</hi> the high Prieſt was alſo created ſecular magiſtrate, for ſo were all the high Prieſtes after the returne of the people from <hi>Babilon,</hi> vntill they were conquered by the Romaines and the kingdome was giuen by them vnto <hi>Herodes</hi> a ſtranger and Idu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing we haue aboundantly prooued in generall, the ſuperioritie of the ciuill magiſtrate ouer all men liu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within their dominions, both by expreſſe places of ſcripture, and authorities of auncient fathers, and alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced the ſubiection of the high Prieſt in the olde law vnto the ciuill Prince, and clearely ſhewed Chriſts kingdom to be ſpirituall and that he gaue none other to <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors, and haue fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered all obiections of the aduerſaries, I will deſcende vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to practiſe and prooue the ſuperioritie of Emperours and <hi>Italian</hi> Kings ouer the Popes and Biſhoppes of Rome by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2432:11"/> the preſcripſion of ſeauen hundreth yeares after Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> kinde of proofe which we Catholickes Romaine exact of the Proteſtants crying vnto them to ſhew their ſucceſſiion. But becauſe <hi>Pighius</hi> the Popes proctor in the ſecular pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy doth ſubiect his client vnto the heathen Emperours,<note place="margin">The Pops ſubiect to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours and Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an kings.</note> I neede fetch my limmitation noe higher then <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the greate the firſt Chriſtian Emperour. Now to ſhew how he baniſhed Biſhoppes perhappes will be thought to ſmall purpoſe, becauſe they doe giue this earthly Empire not vnto the Clergy but onely vnto the Biſhoppe of Rome as Chriſts lieuetenant generall in all cauſes as well ſpirituall as tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.<note place="margin">See for, theſe hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories Paul: Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Platina and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellicus.</note> But I doe finde that his ſonne and ſucceſſor <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> did baniſh <hi>Liberius</hi> the Biſhoppe of Rome becauſe he would not ſubſcribe to the depoſition of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and cauſed another to be c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſen in his place. Moreouer when the Cytie of Rome and the Country of <hi>Italy</hi> came by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt into the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Oſtrogothes</hi> in <hi>Anno Domin. 483.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Liberius.</note> 
               <hi>Theodoricus</hi> the King of the <hi>Oſtrogothes</hi> or of <hi>Italy</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to come before him to <hi>Rauenna</hi> whether he had tranſferred the ſeate of the Empire of <hi>Italy,</hi> leauing the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Rome in the gouernement of the Senate,<note place="margin">Symma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus.</note> And leaſt ſome man vnſkilfull of antiquities ſhould dreame, that it was then the Popes by the donation of Conſtantine, <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doricus</hi> I ſay ſummoned before him at <hi>Rauenna Symmachus</hi> and <hi>Laurentius</hi> who contended for the Biſhopperickes of Rome to the diuiſion of the whole Cytie,<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn.</note> that he as ſoueraing might determine the controuerſy vpon hearing of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And afterward when <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> Emperour of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> had baniſhed the <hi>Arrians</hi> out of all his dominions, <hi>Theodoricus</hi> ſent <hi>Iohn</hi> the byſhoppe of Rome and their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours Embaſſadours vnto <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> willing them in threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſort to tell the Emperour from him that vnleſſe hee did ſpedily reſtore to the <hi>Arrians</hi> theire Churches, and ſuffer them to liue in peace, that he would extinguiſh
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2432:11"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Italy.</hi> They comming to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> honorably receiued by him, did with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> beeing very hoofull for the ſafetie of themſelues and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> countrymen, entreat the Emperour gratiouſly to graunt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nor of their Embaſſage, although it were vniuſt, and to haue regard and compaſſion of <hi>Italy</hi> which otherwiſe would vtterly periſh, with whoſe teares the Emperour beeing mooued granted them their requeſt. But when the Biſhoppe with his aſſociates were returned to <hi>Rauenna</hi> to make relation vnto the King of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours anſwere<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Theodoricus</hi> mooued with malice becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a defender of the Catholicke pietie had receiued him ſo honorably<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> killed him and his fellowes with paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full impriſonment. Then <hi>Theodotus,</hi> annother king of the <hi>Oſtrogothes</hi> ſent <hi>Agapetus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Agapetus</note> the Biſhoppe of Rome Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour as his ſubiect vnto <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the Emperour, which <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> not long after hauing recouered Rome from the <hi>Oſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gothes,</hi> did not by his Lieuetenant, but by his Lieuetenant <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarius</hi> his wife ſpoyle <hi>Siluerius</hi>
               <note place="margin">Silberius:</note> the Biſhoppe of Rome of his Biſhopprick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; Biſhoppes robes: and putting him in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſticall needes confined him into an out Iland Charging him that he would haue betrayed the gate <hi>Aſmaria</hi> that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned vnto his houſe vnto the <hi>Oſtrogothes,</hi> but in deed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes there was ſome other priuie grudge hidden in the Empreſſe her heart. But the manner of the doing doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly declare for how ſmale Princes Popes were reputed in thoſe daies, for <hi>Belſarius</hi> ſending an officer for him the Biſhoppe was brought into his bedde Chamber, becauſe <hi>Belſarius</hi> ſate by his wife who being that day come from <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> wary was laide downe on her bedde. But the proude Dame had no ſooner ſene the Biſhoppe, but ſhe began to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſaide, oh ſirrha wherein haue I or my <hi>Beliſarius</hi> ſo ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e offended your maiſterſhippe, that you ſhould betraye vs vnto the Gothes and immediatly b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d away with him, not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2432:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuffering him to ſpeake one word, And in his roome was one <hi>Vigilius</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vigilius.</note> placed, who not long after refuſing to reſtore vnto his ſeate <hi>Anthenius</hi> who had bene depriued of the Biſhopbricke of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> for the hereſy of <hi>Eutiches; Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odora</hi> the Empreſſe who fauoured <hi>Anthenius</hi> commanded to be arreſted at Rome and ſent priſoner to <hi>Constantinople,</hi> where when being vrged with this vniuſt requeſt he had broken out into this impatient ſpeach that he had thought he had come to <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> but that now he well perceyued it was to <hi>Diocleſian.</hi> He was ſo well whipped for forgetting his leſſon in the two and twentith of Exodus <hi>Non maledices principi populi tui</hi> thou ſhalt not ſpeake ill to the prince of thy people; that he was almoſt ſlaine (I doe thinke noe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian or ciuill Emperour much leſſe <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> woulde ſo ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilely haue v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed him whom he reputed the monarch of the world) and anone after was ignominiouſly drawen along the cyty in a halter and then put in priſon where he continued many yeares with onely breade and water <hi>Anno Domini. 591. Pelagius</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pelagius</note> the Byſhoppe of Rome ſent <hi>Gregory</hi> who ſucceded him in the ſee vnto <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperour of the eaſt, to deſire him not to be offended for that he had ſuffered himſelfe to be denounced Byſhoppe before hee had obtained his conſent and confirmation; for he coulde not ſende before that time to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> becauſe the cytie of Rome had bene ſtraitely beſeiged by the <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards:</hi> Now in thoſe dayes ſaith <hi>Platina</hi> and all other Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians, writing of thoſe times and affaires the election of the Byſhoppe of Rome was voide without the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours aſſent and conformation. And now we are come to <hi>Gregory</hi> himſelfe ſurnamed the greate a man in ſuch credit with the Popes of latter times and the Catholickes Romaine,<note place="margin">Greg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y the great.</note> that they and wee doe more follow him in the diuine ſeruice and ceremonies, then all the reſt that euer ſatte in that ſee before him, and therefore I doe hope
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2432:12"/> that you will the more willingly allowe and embrace his opinion and iudgement of the ſecular ſoueraignytye. As I doe not doubte but yee will cauell at manye of my former examples as vniuſt and tyrannicall, the which I will, not greately ſticke to grant you, and yet they doe ſtrongly prooue the ſuperioritie of thoſe princes, and that they were there lawfull, although lawleſſe ſoueraignes, for as ſubſtantially doe the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmentes of the Catholicke Byſhoppes by the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall Emperours conuince the ſoueraignetie of the Emperours ouer the Byſhoppes: as the confining of the heriticall Byſhoppes by the Catholicke Emperours, Neyther am I leſſe aſſured of the ſubiection of the Byſhoppes of <hi>Aſia</hi> vnto the Emperour of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> for that I reade that <hi>Valens</hi> baniſhed the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Byſhoppes thereof, then I am when I finde that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> baniſhed the <hi>Arrian</hi> Byſhoppes of <hi>Aſia.</hi> For neuer ſhall wee finde that when the Empire was deuided that euer the Emperours of the Eaſt of what Religion ſoeuer they were did banniſh the Byſhoppes of the Weſt nor contrarye wiſe; but eyther dealte onely with them that were vnder their owne Empire, and who would haue a better proofe that this <hi>Iſland</hi> was ſubiect vnto the Romane Empire then the hauocke that <hi>Diocleſian</hi> made here of the Chriſtians, and there Church and doth not he as ſufficientlie ſhew himſelfe to be a lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudge that hangeth vp twenty true men, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hee that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuteth as many theeues: Neither doe wee reade that theſe Emperours and Kinges were reprooued for iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly puniſhing them, ouer whome they had noe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie by right: but becauſe they puniſhed them againſt law and right: for matters that deſerued noe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But leauing this let vs goe to <hi>Gregorie,</hi> who had not learned to date his let<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers as the Popes doe now
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2432:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> with <hi>Anno Pontificatus noſtri</hi> in the yeare of our Popedome but <hi>regnante domino noſtro Mauritio Tiberio piiſſimo Anno decimo quarto, poſt Conſulatum eiuſdem domini noſtri decimo tertio,</hi> in the yeare of the raigne of our Lord <hi>Mauretius Tiberius</hi> the moſt godly Emperour the fourtenth, and after the conſulſhippe of the ſame Lord of ours the thirtenth, as his foure letters in the eccleſiaſticall hiſtory of <hi>Beda</hi> are da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: wherein I doe nore three thinges: firſt that he doth not write the date of his owne creation or inauguration as ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes doe; and ſecondly as ſubiectes doe that he writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the date of the raigne of their Prince: and thirdly that he called him Lord: a worde ſo hautie and high, that <hi>Auguſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> made an edict that noe man ſhoulde call him ſo, noe nor woulde not ſuffer his Children nor Childrens Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to call him ſo,<note place="margin">Suetonius</note> neither in earneſt nor in ſporte. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer with what duetifull humilitie are all his letters fraught that he directeth vnto the Emperour calling him in the plurall number after an vnwonted manner, to declare his vnwonted lowlineſſe and wonted ſubiection. <hi>Domini</hi> my Lordes, and yet becauſe noe man ſhoulde thinke hee called him ſo rather of humilitie then of duetie, it is apparant he vſeth not that tearme to anye other: But writing vnto <hi>Ethelbert</hi> the King of Kent he calleth him in <hi>Beda,</hi> ſonne, a name of obedience and duetifulneſſe, but yet alſo of loue as hee alſo calleth <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lderbert</hi> the King of <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>plaplib. 4. Indicto 12. eplam 96. et 97.</note> But omitting many of his letters I will onely rehearſe ſomewhat out of his threeſcore and one of the ſeconde booke, wherein he fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding greate fault with the Emperour for making an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt Lawe as hee ſaith: that noe Souldiour ſhoulde en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Religion, the which woulde haue made him to haue forgotten all humilitie, if hee had beene as proudly ſpirited as ſome of his ſucceſſors haue beene, he thus beginneth his letters. <hi>Omnipotenti Deo reus eſt qui
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2432:13"/> ſereniſsimis Dominis in omni quod agit &amp; loquitur purus non eſt. Ego autem indignus pietatis veſtrae famulus. &amp;c.</hi> He is guiltie vnto God that is not pure vnto my renowned Lordes in all thinges that he doth and ſpeaketh, but I an vnworthie ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of your godlineſſe, &amp;c. And anone after, <hi>Fatemur Dominis meis,</hi> and <hi>Dominorum pietas ſanxit,</hi> I doe confeſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Lordes, and the godlineſſe of my Lordes hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed. And againe, <hi>Ego vero Dominis meis loquens quid ſum niſi puluis &amp; verniis: ſed tamen quia contra authorem omnium Deum hanc intendere conſtitutionem ſentio Dominis tacere non poſſum.</hi> But I ſpeaking vnto my Lordes what am I but duſt and a worme; but becauſe I do perceiue that this conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth tende againſt God the creator of all, I cannot holde my peace vnto my Lords: Is this the ſpeach of a ſoueraigne or a ſubiect. And a little after. <hi>Ad hac per me ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uum vlti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ſuum &amp; veſtrum reſpondebit Chriſtus dicens, ego te &amp; ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes meos manus tua commiſi, tu a meo ſeruitio milites tuos ſubtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his.</hi> And <hi>ego indignus famulus veſter ſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c.</hi> vnto this will Chriſt himſelf anſwere by me his vileſt bondman and yours, ſaying, I haue aduanced thee from, &amp;c. vnto the empyre, &amp;c. I haue committed my prieſtes into thy handes, and thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt withdraw thy ſouldiours from my ſeruice. And I your vnworthy ſeruant doe knowe. And at the foote of the letter he writeth that which ſtriketh this preſent controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſtone dead: <hi>Ego quidem Iuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ioni ſubiectus eandem legem per diuerſas terrarum partes tranſmitti feci &amp; quia lex ipſa omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti Deo minimè concordat, ecce per ſuggeſtionis meae paginam ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſsimis dominis meis nunciaui, vtribique ergo quae debui exolui, qui &amp; imperatori obedientiam pribus, &amp; pro Deo quae ſenſui mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè tacui:</hi> I beeing ſubiect to commandement haue cauſed the ſame lawe to be ſent through diuers partes of the world, and becauſe the ſame lawe doth nothing agree with God, behold I haue ſignified it vnto my renowned Lorde by the letter of my ſuggeſtion, wherefore I haue in both thinges
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2432:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> diſcharged that which I ought, who haue ſhewed obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto the Emperour, and yet haue neuer a whit left vnſpoken that which I thought in Gods behalfe: In this authoritie I note firſt, that the Pope doth acknowledge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſubiect and ſeruant vnto the Emperour beeing a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and doth call him his leige Lord. Secondlie he doth affirme that God had ſubiected the prieſtes and clergie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Chriſtian princes for to ſerue them: for otherwiſe it can not anſwere the other member: and thou doeſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe thy ſouldiours from my ſeruice: And thirdly that <hi>Gregorie</hi> a Pope doth acknowledge and affirme himſelfe to be ſubiect vnto the Emperours commaundement, yea and thought himſelfe ſo bounde to obey him, that he might not with a ſafe conſcience refuſe to publiſh ſuch decrees of his as he thought in his conſcience vngodly,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lanus diuini ie, that Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gorie offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded not in obeying a wicked &amp; an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> the which thing if any cunning Catholique thinke that <hi>Gregorie</hi> might not lawfully doe, let him reade <hi>Molanus</hi> a learned Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique of <hi>Louayne</hi> his booke <hi>de fide hereticis &amp; rebellibus ſeruanda,</hi> of keeping promiſe with heretickes and rebels, and there he ſhall finde his fact defended, moreouer the like ſubiection of himſelfe and the clergie vnto the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour doth he acknowledge writing of this verie ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Lawe vnto <hi>Theodorus</hi> the Emperours phyſition in theſe wordes words, <hi>Valde autem mihi durum videtur vt ab eius ſeruitio milites ſuos prohibeat, qui ei &amp; omnia tribuit, &amp; domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non ſolùm militibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eplape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib. 2. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. in eplape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lt.</note> 
               <hi>ſed etiam ſacerdotibus conceſſet.</hi> In en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh this, But it ſeemeth to me to be harde that he ſhould forbid his ſouldiours his ſeruice, who hath both gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him all that he hath, and alſo granted him to be Lorde ouer not onely the ſouldiours but alſo the prieſtes. In the ſame letter alſo he doth call the king my Lord; and our Lord. But although I hope that this aſſertion and iudgement of <hi>Grego<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> ſurnamed the great, a Pope, a canonized ſaint, and one of the foure approued Doctors of the latine
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2432:14"/> Church, will ſatisfie all reaſonable Catholickes Romane. Yet I will proceede further with the eccleſiaſticall practiſe. Anone after <hi>Gregorie</hi> and about the yeare of our Lord. 608. <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the third was a very earneſt ſuter vnto <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperour,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Bonifaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</p>
                  <p>Paulus diaconus.</p>
               </note> to decree that the ſea of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhoulde be the heade Church of Chriſtendome, the which at length he obtained with much a doe: but in good faith he might haue ſaued much labour, if he had beene Monarch of the world, for then he could haue done it of himſelfe without once God haue mercy to the Emperour.<note place="margin">Paulus diaconus.</note> And his ſucceſſor <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the fourth put vp a ſupplication to the ſame <hi>Phocas</hi> that he would vouchſafe to commaund that the Temple of <hi>Pantheon</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> which had beene dedicated to all the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan</hi> Gods, ſhould be conuerted to the Church of the virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and of all the holy Martyrs.<note place="margin">Seuerinus</note> I trow this example is of ſome moment, <hi>Anno. 636. Seuerinus</hi> was choſen Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to ratifie the which election ſaith <hi>Sabellicus,</hi> there muſt be had the aſſent of the Emperours Lieuetenant in <hi>Italy,</hi> called the Eparch. <hi>Iſaac</hi> that then had that charge came therefore to <hi>Rome</hi> as he ſaide, but becauſe he woulde be paide for his paines, he tooke out all the treaſure out of the veſtrie of the Laterane Church, deuiding parte of it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his ſouldiours, and ſending parte vnto the Emperour, and leaſt he ſhoulde be called an ill cooke, hee alſo licked his owne fingers; and yet the Pope ſtirred not one whit, ſuch powerleſſe princes were Popes in thoſe daies,<note place="margin">Sabell.</note> and ſuch ſeruile ſubiectes vnto Emperours: Againe aboute <hi>Anno Domini. 650. Conſtans</hi> the Emperour commaunded his Eparch <hi>Olympius</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund vpon their allegeance, <hi>Martin</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> and all the reſt of the <hi>Italian</hi> Biſhops to embrace the hereſy of the Monothlites;<note place="margin">Martin.</note> which if they ſhould refuſe to doe that then hee ſhoulde take order, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> might be taken priſoner; or if that could not be done without great vprore, by reaſon of the good will
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2432:15"/> and defence of the people, (for much was the authoritie and maieſtie of the Emperours decayed with the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> by there farre diſtance, there ſmall Empyre in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> beeing cooped in a narrowe corner, by the <hi>Lomberdes,</hi> their hereſies and vngodlineſſe; and finally becauſe they had made the ſeate of their Lieuetenant to be at <hi>Rauenna</hi>) that then he ſhoulde cauſe him ſodenly to be ſlayne by ſome ſleight, he came to <hi>Rome</hi> declared the Emperours com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, the which the Biſhop refuſed to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh, but to apprehende him the <hi>Eparch</hi> durſt not, and of murdering him he miſſed. But two yeares after <hi>Theodorus</hi> the <hi>Eparch</hi> entered the Citie, apprehended him, ſent him in Irons vnto the Emperour, who confined him into the <hi>Cherſoneſus</hi> of <hi>Thrace,</hi> where for pouertie he periſhed. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. 667.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diac.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtans</hi> the Emperour after he had vnfortunatelie fought in <hi>Italy</hi> with the <hi>Lombardes,</hi> came vnto <hi>Rome</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe <hi>Vitalian</hi> with all the clergie going forth ſixe miles to receiue him, who ſhortly after deceiued them, for hee ſpoyled the Church called <hi>Pantheon</hi> of all the ſacred orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,<note place="margin">Vitalian.</note> and vncouered it taking of the tile of copper, yea and all the auncient pieces of worke, eyther of copper or marble, that he could finde in the whole Citie, and ſent to <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> ſo that he defaced <hi>Rome</hi> more in ſeauen daies, then all the <hi>Barbarians</hi> had euer done ſince the decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Empyre: and the like hauock he made in all the the Churches ſubiect vnto him in <hi>Italy, Sicileye,</hi> and <hi>Sardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> and yet for all this <hi>Peter</hi> drewe not the ſworde, for hee yet remembred how bitterly his maſter had once checked him before for fighting, <hi>Anno Dom. 700. Iuſtinianus</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour (ſaith <hi>Diaconus</hi>) commaunding <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Pope to come vnto him honourably receiued him,<note place="margin">Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tine.</note> and ſent him backe; whom he beeing proſtrated on the ground, deſired to be an interceſſor vnto God for his ſinnes, renewed all the priuiledges of his Church, why then the priuiledges
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2432:15"/> were firſt giuen by the Emperour and not by God himſelfe. But that the Emperour fell downe at the Biſhops feete, it was done in reſpect not of his greatneſſe, but of his godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: a thing vſually done by great princes vnto ancient Monkes and Hermites, renowned for their ſtrict life, and rare pietie, whereof all Chriſtian hiſtories yeelde vs ſtore of examples: and this to be ſoe doth his requeſt of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion vnto GOD for his ſinnes manifeſtly ſhewe. But to returne againe to our practiſe about <hi>Anno Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. 690.</hi> another <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the Emperour ſent <hi>Zacharias</hi> his Protoſpatharius or high Conſtable, into <hi>Italy,</hi> for to bring <hi>Sergius</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sergius.</note> vnto him in Irons, becauſe he woulde not ſubſcribe vnto a lewde counſell helde by him at <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sabell.</note> and he had done it if that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Armie in <hi>Italy</hi> what for hatred of the Emperour, and the good will of the Pope, and his cauſe, had not ſpeedily marched to <hi>Rome,</hi> to withſtand his apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: yet this Emperour did afterwarde renewe for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> the Biſhop a confirmation of all the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iuiledges of the Sea of <hi>Rome:</hi> This <hi>Constantine</hi> was the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (ſaith <hi>Omphrius</hi>) the newe Chronicler of the Popes, <hi>Qui in os auſus eſt reſiſtere,</hi> which durſt reſiſt the Emperours of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to their faces, for he at the importunate petition of the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> who requeſted it with great outcries, decreede that the name of <hi>Philippicus</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſhoulde not be mentioned at the Aulter, nor in anie writing or recordes, nor his image ſet vp in their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, becauſe he had commaunded the Biſhop to conſent vnto his Arrianiſme, and the aboliſhing of the Images of Saintes. But <hi>Paulus Diaconus</hi> who liued neare that time writeth that <hi>ſtatuit populus,</hi> the people decreede, and not the Pope.</p>
            <p>About <hi>Anno Domini. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. Leo Iſauricus</hi> the Emperour commaunded <hi>Gregory</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gregorie the ſecond</note> to deſtroy all the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2432:16"/> images of the Saintes, the which he refuſed to doe. But although the Emperour did execute many therefore, and about that matter baniſhed the patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and had ſundry times practiſed the Popes death, both co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertly, and alſo by open forces, cauſing the Eparch to bring his Armie before the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> where he was repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the <hi>Lombardes;</hi> yet woulde the Pope by no meanes be wonne to conſent that a new Emperour ſhould be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen in <hi>Ital<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> the which was now in a good forwardneſſe, the people hauing ſlaine <hi>Martin</hi> the gouernour of the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> and his ſonne the Lieuetenant of <hi>Campania,</hi> and the Citizens of <hi>Rauenna</hi> the Eparch: and had choſen them almoſt in euerie Citie newe officers: But <hi>Gregorie</hi> woulde by no meanes conſent thereunto, but wonne them to be quiet with much a doe. But when the Emperour woulde not deſiſt from forcing of his edict, for the aboliſhment of Images vppon the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and the <hi>Italians, Gregorie</hi> the third ſucceſſor vnto the other, helde a Counſell in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi> wherein he excommunicated the Emperour, and then the Citizens of <hi>Rome</hi> and all the teritorie about, called by the name of the Duchy of <hi>Rome,</hi> reuolted from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, who was negligent in defending them againſt the <hi>Lombardes,</hi> that had ſweeped him almoſt out of all <hi>Italie,</hi> from <hi>Rome</hi> to the <hi>Alpes,</hi> and ſoe the Pope became prince of the Citie and Duchie of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Sigon. de regno Italiae.</note> and ſubiect vnto no man about the yeare, 730. And to eſtabliſh the ſtate of the Romane principalitie, by ſtopping of titles, <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias</hi> the Pope wonne his Creator <hi>Pepine</hi> the french king to ſpoyle <hi>Aiſtulfus</hi> the king of the <hi>Lombardes</hi> of <hi>Rauenna,</hi> by right whereof, beeing the ſiege of the <hi>Gotiſh</hi> kingdome and the emperiall exarchate in <hi>Italy;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Pope cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> he claimeth tribute of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and for to beſtowe it vppon him and his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, for to take away all quarrell for euer. Thus ye ſee that the Biſhoppes of <hi>Rome</hi> were alwaies ſubiect vnto the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2432:16"/> princes of the Citie, vntill ſuch time as the reuolting people had created him their prince, as all other Biſhops in ciuill ſoueraigne, ſo that the Popes are not exempted of temporall ſubiection by the inſtitution of GOD, but by the election of men; as the high prieſtes became to be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes after the returne of the <hi>Iewes</hi> from <hi>Babylon,</hi> there beeing ordained to be the temporall prince: Then ſeeing by the ordinance of God the Pope was a ſubiect, and by the creation of men beeing made a ſoueraigne, onely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſome certaine prouinces; I cannot ſee howe eyther by Gods Law or mans, hee can rightly claime anie autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to depoſe Chriſtian princes at his pleaſure, no more then any other ſubiecte can his ſoueraigne, or ſeuerall ſoueraignes one another: to grant eyther of which is ſoe abſurde, that I ſhoulde ſhewe my ſelfe to haue verie little witte, if I ſhoulde goe aboute to refute eyther, as though any man that had common ſenſe woulde doubte of them. For to reaſon that <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> becauſe hee is ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſoueraigne ouer theſe prouinces which are called the patrimonie of <hi>Peter,</hi> may therefore depoſe all other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian princes, is as good an argument as if I ſhoulde ſaie, <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> is Queene of <hi>England,</hi> therefore ſhe may depoſe the prince of the patrimonie, and all other Chriſtian princes. So that by prouing my firſt propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that Chriſt gaue vnto <hi>Peter</hi> and his ſucceſſors no ſoueraignetie ſecular, I haue alſo conuinced the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde, that they can not depriue Chriſtian princes of their principalities.<note place="margin">The Pope cannot de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe the temporall ſoueraine</note> Neyther is the Popes claime anie thing aduanced by thoſe two ſayinges of Chriſt vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> which I doe finde alleadged by <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth, when hee firſt of anie Pope depoſed <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, as the warrant of his doings.<note place="margin">Plati.</note> The firſt is feede my ſheepe, wherein hee did not, ſayde <hi>Gregorie</hi> exempt Kinges. And the other, whatſoeuer thou ſhalt binde on
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2432:17"/> the earth, ſhall be bound in Heauen, and whatſoeuer thou doeſt looſe in the earth, ſhall be looſed in Heauen. For I haue proued before that Chriſt his kingdome was ſpirituall; and ſoe a ſpirituall charge of ſoules hee committed to <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors, and noe Empyre ouer the bodies and goods of anie men. But Doctor <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ders</hi> takes greate holde of the Greeke woorde <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Poimaine</hi> which the Apoſtle vſeth when Chriſt bad <hi>Peter</hi> the ſecond time to feede his ſheepe for that worde (ſaith hee) ſignifieth alſo to gouerne. It doth indeede pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlie ſignifie to keepe ſheepe, as we terme it wherein wee include not onelie the feeding of them, but alſo the care of looking to them that they take noe harme, the dreſſing of them when they be ill; and all other thinges belonging to the charge and duetie of a ſheepehearde; and properlie no other ſignification hath it; but by a Metaphore to ſhewe with howe greate care, mildeneſſe and lenitie kinges ought to gouerne their ſubiectes. <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> doe often call kinges ſheepeheardes of the people; and ſo likewiſe the ſacred ſcriptures. In the twentith of the <hi>Actes</hi> we haue the ſame wordes: where we reade, Therefore looke vnto your ſelues, and the whole flocke wherein the holie Ghoſt hath placed you Biſhoppes (and ouerſeers) in greeke poimaine the Church of God which he hath purchaſed him with his bloode. Nowe that the Apoſtles or any Biſhoppes had any ſecular power, <hi>Pighius</hi> himſelfe doth denie, as long as the temporall princes had not receiued the Goſpell: ſo that this worde can by no meanes importe anie earthly ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie. And in this Oration <hi>Paule</hi> doth plainely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, what kinde of kingdome Chriſtes is, when hee ſaith to gouerne the Church of God, which he purchaſed with his bloode: for he purchaſed none with his bloode but t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s ſpirituall kingdome; for as GOD hee was poſſeſſed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Empyre of the whole worlde from the beginning.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2432:17"/> But the place of binding and loſing we haue examined al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie, and proued that it cannot be vnderſtoode otherwiſe then Chriſt himſelfe doth interpret it, in the twenteth of <hi>Iohn,</hi> whoſe ſinnes ye ſhall remitte are remitted; and whoſe ſinnes yee ſhall retaine are retained, and a recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing into the Church and kingdome of heauen, and a ſhutting out of it. And therefore he ſaith; whatſoeuer thou ſhalt binde on earth ſhall be bound in Heauen; and not, ſhall be bounde in earth, leaſt any man ſhould dreame that he gaue <hi>Peter</hi> ſecular power ouer earthly Empires, and that all the commandements and ordinances and decrees of his ſucceſſors, touching worldly matters, ſhould be receiued and kept, throughout the whole world. Neither if the Pope had any ſuch authoritie giuen him by any generall Counſell,<note place="margin">A general counſell cannot depoſe Princes.</note> as I am aſſured he hath not (for as for the canon made in the counſell of <hi>Laterane,</hi> we will anone make a large ſeuerall treatiſe thereof, were it good and ſufficient to binde all Princes to obedience, becauſe it lieth not in the power of a generall counſell to diſpoſe of ſecular matters. For ſeeing generall counſells doe altogether conſiſt of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons eccleſiaſticall, and they doe allow noe temporall prince any voice therein; and that all the Byſhoppes that are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled there, do ſit as Byſhops &amp; ſpirituall Lords, &amp; not as temporal, &amp; that they be ſecular ſubiects, &amp; not ſoueraignes; &amp; that the kingdom of the Church is a diſtincte kingdom, as al the Catholickes ſay, from the kingdomes of the world; It is as abſurd to holde that they can makes lawes touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing temporalities, to be obſerued of all temporall Princes vnder temporall paines; as if a madde man would affirme that the aſſembly of the three ſtates of <hi>France,</hi> may ordaine ſtatutes for the Queenes maieſty of England, &amp; hir realme, and that they are bound in conſcience to obſerue all lawes made there. For doubtleſſe the temporall and the eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall kingdomes are as ſeuerall kingdomes as Englande
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2432:18"/> &amp; France, &amp; which haue more alliance together then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two, becauſe they are both ſecular, both bodilie, both ruled, by one ſword, but of the other the one is ſpirituall, the other bodily, the one of the worlde, the other of heauen; the one ſwayed by the ciuill and materiall ſworde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he other by the ſpirituall, the one ſlaying the ſoule, the other the body. But now I would not haue any fond man to imagine, that I doe goe about to ſpoile the temporall prince of his high prerogatiue, in ordaining of holſome lawes, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the true faith of Chriſt; and the ſincere obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of all the reſt of his holy commandementes; the which I doe thinke him bound in conſcience to doe: but that I doe firmely beleeue and openly profeſſe, that by the right giuen him by God, he may puniſh all perſons, both eccleſiaſticall and temporall, within his dominions, that ſhall offend, either in faith or manners, by fine, impriſonment, baniſhment, confiſcation of landes and goodes, attainder of blood, death, or finally any other temporall paines; as the noble princes of this land haue alwaies vſed to doe. And therefore Iuſtice Brian in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimo</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeauenth doth call the King a mixt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for he is (ſaith <hi>Brian</hi>) a perſon vnited with the prieſts of holy Church. But I denie him the adminiſtration of gods holy ſacraments, and the exerciſe of the ſpirituall ſworde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which I doe appropriate vnto the eccleſiaſticall offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers. Wherefore much leſſe can the Byſhoppes in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall counſell, giue away the crownes of their Kinges; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to the afore rehearſed rule of the Canon law noe man can giue that right vnto another, which he hath not himſelfe. But if there were ordained a bodie politicke of all the Chriſtian princes and ſtates, what they beeing aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in a counſell generall might doe is annother que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, the which we will leaue to bee diſputed of them that ſhall ſee this happe inſtitution. And in the meane time
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2432:18"/> they muſt pardon vs, if we doe not lightly beleeue that the Pope hath power to depoſe Princes; ſeeing wee can finde no warrant therefore, neither in the ſcriptures, the auncient counſells, the olde fathers, the practiſe of the Church of God, neither before Chriſt, neither ſeauen hundreth years after him, although there raigned many Idolatrous, hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and wicked Princes. Of the Iewiſh Kinges verye few were good, but rather ſuch men as GOD had ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commaunded that they ſhoulde not ſpare, if they were their Brothers, or ſuch a friende as hee looued as deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as his owne ſoule; but that his hand ſhould bee firſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him to ſtone him to death, and yet wee doe not reade that any one of them was depoſed, by the high Prieſtes, or his ſubiectes; armed againſt him by them: And yet were they ſo zealous men of their dignitie, that they would in noe wiſe ſuffer the King to vſurpe ought vppon him, in ſo much that one of them openly withſtoode <hi>Ozias</hi> the King,<note place="margin">The hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of king Ozias handled.</note> that woulde vnlawfully execute his office, in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring incenſe vnto GOD; neither doth the expelling of this King out of the temple by rhe Prieſtes, becauſe God had for his proude part ſtricken him with leproſie, and that thereupon hee ſequeſtred himſelfe from companie, and left the gouernement of matters of ſtate vnto his ſonne, prooue ought againſt the prerogatiue of Princes,<note place="margin">The text ſaith 2. Coro. 26.20. that they cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed haſtily to depart thence &amp; he was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to goe out.</note> as the Engliſh authour of the eccleſiaſticall diſcipline doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre. For hee was not expelled out of the temple be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee offred incenſe, but becauſe the wraith of GOD had made him a leper, the which kinde of men by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commaundement of GOD might not conuerſe with other. And if wee will receiue the report and aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> a learned Prieſt and hiſtorian of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the prieſtes did not thruſt him out of the temple, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed him to depart, the which hee did ſoone obey when he ſaw himſelfe made ſo loathſome on a ſodaine &amp; was
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2432:19"/> aſtonied with the manifeſt wraith of God; and hereunto the text ſeameth to aſſent which ſaith and haſtily they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled him &amp;c. But he himſelfe alſo made haſt to goe out, becauſe he had preſently felt the plague or ſtrooke of God. But that he was as ſome ſeeme to ſay, depoſed of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome therefore, we doe reade neither in the ſcriptures, nor in <hi>Ioſephus.</hi> But onely this ſaith <hi>Paralyp.</hi> So King <hi>Ozias</hi> was a leeper euen to his dying day, and dwelt in an houſe by himſelfe, becauſe he was full of leproſie, for the which he had beene caſt out of the houſe of the Lord, Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more <hi>Ioathan</hi> his ſonne gouerned the kings houſe, and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the people of the land. And almoſt the ſame words wee reade in the booke of the kings, Soe that by the wordes of the text it doth not appeare that he was either depoſed or did giue vp the Kingdom, but onely abandoned al reſort, by reaſon of his contagious ſickneſſe and ignominy, gaue vp the maneging of matters of ſtate and the princely port vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ſonne, and ſo accordingly whoſoeuer doth marke diligently the ſupputiaton of yeares, which the booke of the Kings maketh, ſhall manifeſtly ſee, that he reckoneth <hi>Ozias</hi> his raigne euen vntill his dying day. Neither if that <hi>Ozias</hi> had beene depoſed becauſe of his leproſy, would it ſoe much further theire cauſe, as they faine in ſaying that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy is inward leproſy, then, Idolatry is. And yet can they not finde that euer any King of the <hi>Iewes</hi> was depoſed by the high Prieſt for Idolatry, nor any Chriſtian prince by the Pope for any cauſe for the ſpace of ſeauen hundreth yeares after Chriſt, although thoſe times yeelded many vngodly Princes, as we haue ſhewed you before of Emperours, one flatly fallen, from the faith vnto <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> ſundry <hi>Arrians,</hi> ſome <hi>Monothlets,</hi> and <hi>Eutiches,</hi> and many cruell perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Catholickes. And ſo likewiſe many of the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrogothes</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> were <hi>Arrians,</hi> and many moe in the ſame prouince of the Lombard kinges. And yet a farre longer
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2432:19"/> race of the Weſtgotiſh Kings in Spaine. But if any man will rubbe his face and ſay, that the Byſhoppes of Rome in thoſe ages eyther had not ſo much knowledge in the worde of GOD, or elſe ſo greate zeale as there ſucceſſors ſince, all men that ſhall heare them will ſhoute at them. They write that when <hi>Nero</hi> whipped Senatoures, execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted noble men, ſpoyled Citizens, waſted prouinces, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe or colour, and finally in all things made his luſt law: he triumphing at this iolitie, boaſted that neuer any man before him did know what an Emperour might doe.<note place="margin">Act. 5.</note> Certes the holy and learned fathers, in ancient time knew not this diuinitie, that when there princes wrongfully op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed them, they ſhould ſtraightway caſt off their yoke, but rather patiently beare whatſoeuer ill ſhould be inflicted on them for Gods cauſe.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> They remembred that the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les from whom they ſet their light and learning, being whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped at a conuocation of the Iewiſh Priſtes and Elders, went away reioycing becauſe they were counted worthie to ſuffer reproach for the name of Ieſus.<note place="margin">Athanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in epla. 2. ad vlit vit Agent</note> They had not forgotten the ſaying of their Sauiour <hi>Mat. 5.</hi> Bleſſed are they that ſuffer perſecution for righteouſneſſe; for theires is the Kingdome of heauen. Ye are bleſſed when men ſhall curſe you, and perſecute you, and lying, ſhall ſay all manner of euill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you for me. Reioyce and be glad becauſe your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in heauen is abundant: for ſo they perſecuted the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that were before you. When <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Emperour vrged <hi>Hoſius</hi> the holy Byſhoppe of <hi>Cordu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> the Byſhoppe of Rome his deputy, and the three hundreth Byſhoppes aſſembled at <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dica,</hi> with bitter ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment (as he had alreadie ſerued many of there colled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) vnleſſe they would ſubſcribe to the wicked errour of <hi>Arrius:</hi> they all refuſed to doe it, but they did not menace the Emperour with depoſition, if hee woulde not relinquiſh his falſe faith, and reuoke the godly baniſhed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2432:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> Byſhoppes: bur contrariwiſe confeſſed vnto him. <hi>Non no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s fas eſt imperium in te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riis tenere</hi> it is not lawfull for vs to holde Empire on the earth. And not withſtanding all his hurtfull wickedneſſe; yet they affirmed that he that ſhould caſt but a malignant eye at his Empire did reſiſt the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God; ſo farre were they from thinking that his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes might openly take armes againſt him. <hi>Don Iohn De Auſtria</hi> in his warres in the low Cuntries,<note place="margin">Don Iohns enſignes.</note> bare in his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne a deuiſe of a croſſe with this word. <hi>In hoc ſigno vici<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Turcos, in h c ſigno vincam hereticos,</hi> with this ſigne I ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Turkes, with this ſigne I will vanquiſh the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes: ſo if the latter Popes had ſaide, with this vertue and weapon of patience, our anceſtors ouercame the heathen, and heriticall Emperours; and with the ſame we will ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Emperours that will intrude vppon our tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, perhappes their ſtate had not bene now ſo ſtaggering: for whoſoeuer ſhall marke the courſe of the hiſtory of the Church of God, ſhall finde that it hath growen greate by patience, but hath rather decreaſed then encreaſed by armes and violence. Moreouer if the Popes will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to reade their old recordes, they ſhall ſee and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande that ſuch of their predeceſſors as armed themſelues with patience, and vſed none other but the ſpirituall ſword and that alſo ſparingly and ſeldome; were had of all men in greater reputation and reuerence, and could doe more in the world, then their ſucceſſors, that after the ſpirituall ſword which Chriſt had deliuered vnto them ſharpe and dreadfull to be vſed onelie in extremitie, &amp; but in his cauſe &amp; quarell, had through there continuall abuſing and drawing at euery light priuate braule, became ſo hagled, blunt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, that euery boy laught at it, did furiouſly fall to catching of the ſecular ſworde out of the temporall magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates hand. Like as they report of <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſeconde whether meerely deuiſed or done in deede I (ſaith <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rou</hi>)
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2432:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> know not: that when he went in perſon into the fielde againſt the French, armed with a paire of keyes in his hande, and a ſworde by his ſide, hee threw his keyes into the riuer of Tiber, and therewith all draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſworde ſaide: ſeeing <hi>Peters</hi> keyes haue done noe good, Paules ſworde ſhall helpe mee. And ſurely therein the Pope fared like, Ioakin the King of Iuda who truſted in a rotten reede the king of <hi>Egypt</hi> to defende him againſt the <hi>Aſſyrian:</hi> And ſo they incurred with him the curſe pronounced in that place by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Princes neuer came of charitie.</note> Curſed is the man that truſteth in man and maketh fleſh his arme. And becauſe Cardinall <hi>Hoſius</hi> will haue <hi>Luthers</hi> doctrine tried, whether it bee good or bad by the roote that bredde it, I pray let vs alſo ſee from what roote this practiſe of depoſing of Princes did ſpring. There be two rootes ſaith <hi>Aguſtine</hi> vppon <hi>Iohn,</hi> and out of him <hi>Hoſius,</hi> which two huſbandmen the holie Ghoſt and the deuill, ſet in mans hart, the one charitie or loue, the other inordinate deſire;<note place="margin">Henry.</note> of the one commeth all good of the other all ill, now whether of theſe rootes brought forth depoſition of Princes I praye let vs conſider. The firſt Pope that did it in practiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Anno Domini 108<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> was <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth Emperour, becauſe he being exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the Pope, for excommunicating of fiue of his chiefe counſellours; whome he thought ruled him to much, and for commaunding him vppon paine of excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to appeare before him at Rome, the tweſday in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond weeke of Lent; to purge himſelfe of ſuch chrimes as his rebellious ſubiectes the <hi>Saxons</hi> had accuſed him of;<note place="margin">See Plati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na and Sigonius.</note> had called a counſell in <hi>Germany</hi> where <hi>Gregory</hi> was depoſed being accuſed there by <hi>Hugh Blancke</hi> a Cardinall, and many <hi>Italian</hi> Byſhoppes, of Necromancy, hereſy, lecherie ſymony, tiranny, and I know not what elſe, nor force how
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2432:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> truely: but moſt true it is, that this was the cauſe of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours depoſing, as it doth appeare by the Popes bull wherein wee finde theſe wordes. Becauſe he hath too audaciouſly and raſhly laid hands on the Church (the Pope ſpeakes to <hi>Peter</hi>) and becauſe he hath not obeyed my au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie as becommeth a Chriſtian. &amp;c. therfore in thy name I do accurſe him, depoſe him, diſcharge all men of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towardes him, and forbid them to obey him, that all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may know that thou art <hi>Peter.</hi> &amp;c. Now to depoſe the Emperour becauſe he had cauſed him to be depoſed, was this charitie or inordinate deſire of reuenge? did any of his predeceſſors before him the like? God ſaith reuenge is mine, &amp; I will repey it: and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> charitie ſeeketh not hir owne. I pray you tel me what Charity was it towards the Church &amp; Chriſtendom, rather then he would forſake his ſea, yea or reuoke his cholericke cenſure, that he would ſee all <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Sabel</note> almoſt vtterly deſtroyed by ciuill warres, his fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in <hi>Germany</hi> broken in ſeauen blody battelles, his two Idol Emperours ſlaine, and all the forces of his Italian ſtaffe &amp; ſtay, the mightie counteſſe <hi>Mawde</hi> vtterly defayted; great part of the Citizens of Rome conſumed by three yeares ſeige, the <hi>Burgo San: Pietro</hi> twiſe ſacked and defaced, all the houſe of the Corſy, the nobleſt Citizens of Rome and his faſteſt friendes raced to the grounde: the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of the world the ſeptiſolium, taken and deformed, his nephew taken priſoner, the cyty of Rome twiſe ſette on fire, by Suiſcardo, whom being excommunicated &amp; now reconciled, he had procured to come to diſcharge him out of the caſtle of <hi>San. Angelo:</hi> with two huge waſtes, remaine yet to be ſeene at this day in the fayreſt part of the Cytie for a perpetuall reproch for the firſt depoſing of Princes: &amp; yet woulde not his ſtoute heart ſtoupe, but when at the importunate prayers of the oppreſſed Romaines, hee had graunted to receiue the Emperour into grace vppon his
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2432:21"/> ſubmiſſion, he afterward vtterly refuſed it, becauſe the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens requeſted, that the Emperour might doe it, in his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall robes and fled firſt into the Caſtle <hi>San: Angelo,</hi> and afterward vnto <hi>Salerne,</hi> where he died in voluntarie baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not daring to abide at <hi>Rome,</hi> for feare of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens who for theſe manifolde calamities with which he had ouerwhelmed them, did deadly hate him. What an hard heart had he, that would not relent at ſo many and extreeme miſchieues and miſeries? Did he not bluſh to remember how the noble <hi>Quintus Metellus</hi> a pagane, being wrongfully forbididden fyre and water by <hi>Apulieus</hi> the <hi>Tribune</hi> of the commonaltie, to be reuenged on <hi>Meitellus</hi> for putting him out of the ſenate for his lewde life; choſe rather willingly to go into banniſhment, hauing the ſtronger faction, then that any tumult ſhould be ſtirred vp in the Citie for him. Againe how many of his predeceſſors did for righteouſnes ſake ſuffer baniſhment, impriſonment, yea and painfull death, when they might haue ſhrowded and ſaued themſelues, we haue alreadie ſhewed by many examples. And alſo <hi>Marcellinus</hi> a pagane doth report, that <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Emperour coulde hardlie in the dead time of the night carrie <hi>Liberius</hi> out of the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> with great difficulty, for the good will of the people that burned in his loue: ſo that it is likelie that if the Biſhop would with force haue reſiſted, he woulde haue beene to hot and to heauy for the Emperour to carry away. But neyther God nor Deuill had yet reueeled vnto the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> this newe dignitie of <hi>Gregories:</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Plati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na and Sigon.</note> that they could by Apoſtolicall power binde all men, not onely in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite but alſo in bodie, and all the goods of fortune: that they might depoſe Emperorus for their pride &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumacy, in not obeying of their commaundementes as <hi>Gregorie</hi> did <hi>Henry,</hi> and giue the Empyre vnto another, for his humilitie and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, as <hi>Gregorie</hi> did to <hi>Rodulph,</hi> becauſe he had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to giue his ſonnes pledges for aſſurance that he wolde
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2432:22"/> ſtand to the Popes arbiterment: for they yet knewe not this reaſon that <hi>Gregorie</hi> alleadged quite voyde of reaſon, in theſe wordes. Wherefore (O <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paule</hi>) the moſt holy and chiefe of the Apoſtles, confirme by your authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that which I haue ſpoken, that all men may nowe at the length vnderſtand, that if ye can binde and looſe in heauen, that then we alſo can in earth take away, and giue Empieres and Kingdomes, and whatſoeuer elſe men haue. For if ye can iudge thoſe thinges which doe appertaine to God, what is to be thought we may doe, in theſe inferior and prophane thinges? And if it belong to you to iudge Angels, that raigne ouer proude princes, what is it ſeemely that we doe with their bondmen? Therefore let kinges and all princes of the worlde learne by this Emperous example what ye can doe in heauen, and how great ye are with God, and hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth feare to contemne the commaundementes of the holy Church. Doubtleſſe theſe words (now at length may learne) and (henceforth may feare) were very ſignificantly put in by <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gorie,</hi> for indeed before this time, this doctrine was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to the world, as alſo that learned <hi>Hermite</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> the Popes Chronicler <hi>Omphrius,</hi> a man inferior to none in the knowledge of the <hi>Romane</hi> antiquities, doth confeſſe in his booke of Cardinals in theſe wordes: Biſhops cardinales did at the firſt take their place among other Biſhoppes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the anciency of their creation; but afterward by little and little they came to take place aboue all Biſhoppes, Archbiſhops, Metropolitans, Primates &amp; Patriarkes, which began to be vſed by little and little, about the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth, &amp; <hi>Vrbane</hi> the ſecond in which times the election of the Pope (whoſe authority did then begin to be ſupreame as well in ſpirituall thinges as temporall, the Emperours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing depreſſed or trodden downe) was taken out of the hands and power of the Emperours, and granted eſpecially to the Cardinals. And anone after a Prieſt Cardinall was a meane
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2432:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> place between a Biſhop &amp; other Prieſtes not Cardinals. But in the time of <hi>Alexander</hi> the third vnder whom the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was aduanced to the higheſt top or ſtep in earth, the moſt mighty Emperour <hi>Fredericke Redbeard,</hi> &amp; he alſo a moſt infeſtious foe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> being trode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder foot, &amp; vanquiſhed, and forced to deſire peace of the Church: then firſt contrariwiſe Prieſt Cardinals were made of Biſhops, for the dignity of the Cardinals did ſtil grow with the dignity of the Church &amp; Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> but that was greateſt in thoſe daies. Thus farre <hi>Omphrius.</hi> But becauſe <hi>Platina</hi> &amp; others do affirme, that the Pope &amp; the Emperour firſt fell out, about ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony or inueſting of Biſhops, let vs ſee how iniuriouſly here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the Pope dealt with the Emperour. It doth appeare both by the Bookes of the canon law &amp; alſo by <hi>Sigonius</hi> and other hiſtorians the Popes chiefe fauourers, that Pope <hi>Hadria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> gaue vnto <hi>Charles</hi> the great the king of the french men, &amp; Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; <hi>Leo</hi> the eight vnto <hi>Otho</hi> the great the king of the Tuiſchtmen &amp; Emperour for euer the inueſture of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; of al other Biſhops, within their dominions decreeing that no Biſhop choſen by the clargy and people ſhould be conſecrated, vnleſſe he were firſt nominated &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſted (that is had the croſier and ring deliuered him) by the Emperour, this authority &amp; priuiledge enioied al Emperours from <hi>Charles</hi> the great vnto this <hi>Henry</hi> being the 17 in ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and that he vſed it no otherwiſe it is aparant by the elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Biſhop of <hi>Cullen</hi> by the clergy &amp; the people, a little while before this broile, wherof we do read mention made in <hi>Lambertus Snatchburgenſis.</hi> A thing alwaies vſed in <hi>England,</hi> that neyther Biſhop nor Abot, ſhould be choſen without a <hi>conge de ler,</hi> or licence to choſe, firſt obtained of the king, nor reputed for Biſhop before the king had confirmed him. So likewiſe <hi>Hoſius contra Brentium</hi> doth affirme, that the kings of <hi>Poland</hi> haue alwaies had the nominating of all Biſhps with in their kingdom. Now of this ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t part of his patrimony of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2432:23"/> the Empyre, would <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſpoyle <hi>Henry,</hi> yea and all lay men, making a decree that he ſhould be accurſed, that did take any eccleſiaſticall dignitie or benefice, at the hande of any lay man,<note place="margin">See Plati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na and Sabell.</note> and did alſo excommunicate the lay man that ſhould giue any, nowe I pray you which of them two, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt charitie? <hi>Henry</hi> that for quietneſſe ſake was conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to looſe the right which he and his anceſtors had ſo long time held, in confirming of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> in the cauſe and bloodie ſchiſme of <hi>Alexander, Gregories</hi> immediate predeceſſor? or <hi>Gregorie</hi> that was not contented and ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this rare indulgence of the Emperour, in one and the greateſt Biſhoppricke, but would depoſe him vnleſſe he would alſo ſurrender his right in all the reſt, &amp; eyther would haue his wil or elſe would ſet all Chriſtendome in an vprore? And put caſe he had ſolde two or three ſmall Biſhopprickes as his enemies did charge him for, the great electors ſees, they themſelues beeing his enemies confeſſed he had not ſold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was that a ſufficient cauſe to make him forſake him and his ſucceſſors, for euer an ancient right and inheritance, belonging to the emperiall crowne, as the preſenting vnto benefices, is an inheritance of many ſecular ſubiectes? And could the Church of Chriſt be ſo much endamaged therby, as with thirtie yeares bloodie warres, in all partes of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> through the troubles whereof, neyther the Popes nor other Biſhoppes could employ their functions? But letting this paſſe;<note place="margin">Philippe.</note> the next depoſition was of <hi>Philip</hi> the Emperour for inuading <hi>Peters</hi> patrimony, before he was Emperour, and while he was duke of <hi>Tuſcan.</hi> But becauſe ſome will ſay he was neuer Emperour, becauſe through the Popes menaces but fiue of the electors had choſen him, we will let him paſſe and come vnto <hi>Otho</hi>
               <note place="margin">Otho.</note> the Duke of <hi>Saxon:</hi> whom two of the electors afterward at the great inſtance of the Pope, had choſen Emperour, and whom he almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after he had crowned him depoſed, becauſe he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaded
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2432:23"/> the landes of his puple and vaſſall the king of <hi>Naples.</hi> Did this come of charitie or of a priuate quarrell? It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant that the Popes vſed not nor now doe to cenſure anie prince, for enuading of his neighbour, vnleſſe he were a vaſſal or priuiledged prince of his. And then to make vp the good, three comes on a row <hi>Fredelicke</hi> the ſecond Emperour,<note place="margin">Frederick</note> and alſo king of <hi>Naples,</hi> for inueſting of Biſhoppes in <hi>Naples,</hi> and leuying money of the clergie. And after the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie was ended, againe, becauſe he did not performe his vow to goe into the holy land; and that alſo ſatisfied for making warres againſt the rebellious <hi>Lombardes,</hi> or to make the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie worſt of it, for practiſing with the <hi>Frangipanes</hi> and other <hi>Romanes</hi> to reuolt from the Pope, whom he diſtruſted, did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly ayde his rebelles in <hi>Lombardy.</hi> And did not fleſh and blood and priuate reuenge raigne in all theſe actions? were any of theſe cauſes ſo weightie, that for them ſhould be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp the pernicious factions of <hi>Guelſes</hi> and <hi>Ghibbelines?</hi> to ſet at enmitie for euer, not onely euery prince<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> prouinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Citie of <hi>Italy</hi> but alſo euery name and familie, for to embrace their murdering ſwordes. The laſt depoſed Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour was <hi>Lewes</hi> the fourth,<note place="margin">Lewes. See Plati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na and Nauill.</note> becauſe he intermedled in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> before the Pope had crowned him (a vſuall thing) and that which was the very cauſe indeede, becauſe he openly profeſſed himſelfe a fauourer of the <hi>Ghibbelines,</hi> and namely the vicecount whom the Pope deadly hated, and had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated for taking armes againſt the <hi>Guelſes,</hi> and put the <hi>Florentines,</hi> and the <hi>Neopolitanes</hi> and the other <hi>Guelſes</hi> in feare, leaſt he would ſaith <hi>Platina</hi> ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct of them <hi>Iura imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a</hi> the rightes belonging to the Empyre. And who ſeeth not heere partiality and not charitie? Moreouer <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note place="margin">Peter.</note> the king of <hi>Aragon</hi> was depoſed and his kingdom of <hi>Aragon</hi> giuen vnto <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Valois</hi> the <hi>French</hi> kinges brother, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had receiued the <hi>Sicilians,</hi> reuolting from the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Charles</hi> the Duke of <hi>Aniou</hi> whom the Pope had placed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2432:24"/> prince there. And doth not alſo ſmell of priuate reuenge? Is this the common good, that <hi>Pighius</hi> beareth vs in hand, the Church of Chriſt reapeth by this prerogatiue of the Pope, that he doth therby reuenge the priuate diſpleaſures of himſelfe, his friendes and vaſſalls. At the ſame time the french king <hi>Philip le Beau,</hi> had ſpoyled <hi>Edward</hi> the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, king of <hi>England</hi> iniuriouſly of the greateſt parte of <hi>Guienne,</hi> and alſo <hi>Guy</hi> the Eare of <hi>Fuaunders</hi> almoſt of his whole Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and was not depoſed therefore. The cauſe is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, <hi>Sicily</hi> was held of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Guienne</hi> nor <hi>Flaunders.</hi> But although he eſcaped ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>free for theſe wronges, and the long detayning in priſon the Earle of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> and two of his ſonnes, yet he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of his kingdome by Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight,<note place="margin">Philip the faire.</note> for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning of a french Biſhop, that rayled at him and mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him, when he coulde not winne him to grant to goe with an Army into the holy land, on the which meſſage the Pope had ſent him vnto the king as ſaith <hi>Platina.</hi> But the french Chronicles report that the king cauſed him to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended at home, at his owne houſe, for that he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode, that he vſed often to ſpeake very ill of him, and to rayle outragiouſly on hm, and deliuered him vnto his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the Biſhop of <hi>Tolouſe</hi> to puniſh him with his aduiſe. The kingdome of <hi>France</hi> was giuen vnto <hi>Albert</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, perhappes for a reward of his wickedneſſe in ſlaying of his ſoueraigne <hi>Adolph</hi> the Emperour; for other puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I doe not finde that Pope did put him vnto therefore.<note place="margin">See Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mog. lib. 3. in Al. 2.</note> But yet I doe not doubt but the fault was more heinous then empriſoning of a Biſhop, for rayling againſt his prince and Lord. Yea and that God did ſo account it he made it manifeſt vnto the worlde by his ſeuere puniſhment of all the conſpiratours. For <hi>Albert</hi> himſelfe was murdered by his owne Coſen germane; the Archbiſhop of Ments founde deade ſitting in his chaire. The Biſhop <hi>Staſburge</hi> was ſlaine
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2432:24"/> by a peſant at <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>nge</hi> in <hi>Briſgow.</hi> The Earle of <hi>Linengen</hi> died ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de. The Earle of <hi>Sweibrucken</hi> was drowned in a riuer. The Earle of <hi>Ochſenſtein</hi> had his deaths wound in the battell. And the Earle <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gerloch</hi> was ſlaine on the way by <hi>Otho</hi> the Duke of <hi>Danao.</hi> But to proceede <hi>Lewes</hi> th 12 of <hi>France</hi> was excommunicated, denounced a ſciſmatike, and his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and goods expoſer for a common ſpoyle to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and the like penalty pronounced on all them that did or ſhould take his part or ayde him.<note place="margin">Lewes the twelfih.</note> And therefore <hi>Iohn</hi> the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> loſt his kingdome, for procuring of a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall counſell, to be called and held, without the conſent of the Pope againſt the Pope that there his infeſtious foe <hi>Iul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> the ſecond might be depoſed, &amp; an other more frendly placed in his roome. And doth not this altogether ſmell of priuate reuenge and not of charity? But perhaps you will ſay, it was a foule part of him, that would be called the moſt Chriſtian king, to ſow ſedition and ſciſme throughout all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for his owne priuate quarrell: and that this doing of his was ſo ill thought of, by moſt of the pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſtendome, that they entred therefore into league againſt him, and had almoſt ſet him beſides his ſaddle. In truth I can neyther prayſe the practiſe nor the pollicie of the French, who ſought to repreſſe the iniurious attemptes of the Pope againſt him rather by colour of lawe, to the diſturbance of all Chriſtendome then by armes, and inuading the Popes territories (as <hi>Philippe</hi> the moderne king of <hi>Spayne</hi> wiſely did in the like caſe) and fondely thought it leſſe enuyous,<note place="margin">Anno Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini. 556.</note> and more agreeable vnto his ſurname of the moſt Chriſtian king, which his anceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs had purchaſeſed, by defending the Popes and <hi>Peters</hi> patrimony with armes; to rayſe vp a ſciſme, then to force the Pope to frindſhip by materiall force.</p>
            <p>But that the Pope compelled him to this outrage, all writers doe confeſſe. For firſt contrary to the league
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2432:25"/> made at <hi>Cambray,</hi> betweene him &amp; the Emperour, the <hi>French</hi> king, the king <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Ferara,</hi> againſt the <hi>Venetians</hi> who had encroched vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he hauing gotten all that he claimed,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee Iouius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n vita Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>honſ. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uiciardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o.</note> not onely made peace with the <hi>Venetians,</hi> without the conſent of his confederates, but alſo exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and with armes enuaded the faſt friend of the <hi>French,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Ferara,</hi> becauſe that he not hauing yet recouered all his right of them, would not ceaſe to moleſt the <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> And alſo he left no ſtone vnturned, to turne the <hi>French</hi> out of <hi>Milan</hi> an <hi>Genna,</hi> the which he at the length brought to paſſe. And was not he then the author of all his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie? Moreouer this Popes brothers ſonne, Duke of <hi>Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine</hi> cruelly murdered of emulation <hi>Alidoſius</hi> a Biſhop, a Cardinall,<note place="margin">See Iouius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n vit. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſ &amp; Guic. Boleſlaw.</note> and Legate of <hi>Bologna,</hi> almoſt in the Popes ſight, and was put to no penance therefore. But <hi>Boleſlaw</hi> the hardie king of <hi>Poland,</hi> was depriued by Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth of his kingdome, and alſo the country of the honour to haue a king (in the which diſhonour it continued 200 yeares) f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ying with his owne hande in his fury <hi>Staniſlaw,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Craccow</hi> for excommunicating him, yea and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicting the whole Citie of <hi>Craccow,</hi> to make him the more odious, becauſe he openly kept another mans wife, and for adultery, a thing which as it ſhould ſeeme by <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus,</hi> as common in <hi>Poland</hi> in thoſe daies as the cart way. Yea thoſe noble women that were honeſt were forced to forſake there owne howſes,<note place="margin">See Cro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>merus hiſt. Pola. lib. 4.</note> for feare of force and rauiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yea and it was common in <hi>Italy</hi> and paſſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed in meaner men, then princes. But yet in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie trueth the kinges fact was verie foule, and made worſe by the furie of his fellowes that chopped in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the ſlayne corpes and caſt it to the crowes. And yet perhaps <hi>Dauid</hi> did almoſt all ill in defiling of a noble mans bed, while he was in his ſeruice in the fielde, and afterward commaunding him to be murdered for his amendes, (but ſo
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2432:25"/> dealt not Boliſlawe with Staniſlaw; and if the qualities of the perſons be not equall, then the manner of the doing doth ouermatch, the one being done without any prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and of aduiſed malice, the other vppon a greate ignominy &amp; vnwonted with kinges, offered him and vpon a ſodaine, while his blood was hotte. which ſeauen yeares continuall abſence from his countrie in forraine warres a little before had ouerheated. And yet <hi>Dauid</hi> loſt not his Kingdome therefore: Neither doe we reade of any realme interdicted for murdering of their Kinges, whereof we haue almoſt infinite examples; or any man depoſed for intrud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into them by ſuch wickedneſſe, vnleſſe perhappes the murdered Prince were the Popes vaſſall. Soe that this zeale in ſeuere puniſhing of princes for miſuſing them of the clergy, I feare me may be imputed rather to a partiall fauour towardes them of their owne coate, and done for their owne ſecuritie, then for zeale of Iuſtice. Like as our Sargeants at London are an hunded times more hotte to haue one hanged that hath ſlaine the baſeſt Yeoman of theires, then another that hath murdered his maiſter, or the beſt noble man within the land. <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh King flew his father in the feilde, and had noething ſaid vnto him therefore; but was excommunicated for aiding of his auncient Alie the french King; whome the Pope lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not, neither could his lamentable loſſe of life in that quarrel quench the Popes Choler, but that he perſecuted him when he was deade long time, denyning his deade body buriall; but yet that is noe ſinne againſt the holy ghoſt, for to aide on denounced a ſciſmatike by the Pope, nor to beare armes againſt the captaine of a croyſy it doth appeare by that we doe reade in <hi>Mariners</hi> his hiſtorie of <hi>Spayne;</hi> when <hi>Peter</hi> the king of <hi>Aragon</hi> comming to ayde the Earle of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe,</hi> and the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> againſt whom the Pope had ſent a croyſy was ſlaine in battell by the Earle of <hi>Monsfort</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2432:26"/> of the Croyſy, and that he would not deliuer <hi>Iames</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Peter,</hi> who was brought vp with him and ſhoulde haue maried his daughter, but for this miſchance vnleſſe he would ſweare that he would not reuenge his fathers, death, the Pope vpon complaint forced <hi>Monſfort</hi> by ſharpe cenſures of excommunication, to ſet him at libertie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſuch promiſe, that the Pope (it was <hi>Iuno Centius</hi> the third) might ſhew that he was annother God that woulde haue mercy where he woulde, and be mercifull to whome it pleaſed him, and that he doth nothing of deſert but all <hi>motu proprio,</hi> as they vſe to ſay; but yet perhappes he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed grace vnto <hi>Iames</hi> for his fathers, <hi>Peters</hi> ſake, who had purchaſed before hand his pardon for dying in the feilde, in the ſuccour of a ſciſmaticke and heretike by being crowned at Rome by the Pope with a crowne made of ſinging breade or wafers, and by graunting vnto the Pope the right to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto all eccleſiaſticall lyuings. But to returne againe to the depoſing of Princes. <hi>Iohn</hi>
               <note place="margin">King Iohn</note> the king of this land, bereft both of kingdome, and life, <hi>Arthur</hi> his elder brothers ſonne, who had bene ordained and proclamed here apparant by common conſent, and kept his Siſter with duble iniury in perpetuall priſon, and eſcaped ſcotfree at the Popes handes: but when he would not accept for Archbiſhoppe <hi>Simon Langton</hi> a Cardinall of the Church of Rome, aduanced to that office through the Popes extraordinary dealing, hee had his whole realme interdicted (which ſuſtained no harme for accepting him for King againſt right) and alſo himſelfe was depoſed therefore. And what reaſon was there but that the King might aſwell maintaine for Archbyſhoppe the Byſhoppe of <hi>Norwich</hi> the faithfull preſident of his counſell, and a man whom the Pope coulde not iuſtly miſlike being firſt choſen at Ganterburye by the Prior, &amp; almoſt the whole couent as the Pope <hi>Simon Langton</hi> his Cardinall choſen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the other, &amp; at Rome by a few of the couent that I may omitte that noe Byſhop could euer be choſen in this realm,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2432:26"/> without the Kings licence, nor being choſen counted Byſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oppe before the King had confirmed him. And if the Pope ſaid that the couent choſe <hi>Norwitch</hi> at Canterbury for feare of the King, becauſe they had firſt elected their ſuperior: might not the King as truely ſay that they choſe <hi>Langton</hi> at Rome for feare of the Pope, for did he not force them to a new election, yea &amp; threatned them who were afraid of the kings diſpleaſure if they choſe not <hi>Langton</hi> if <hi>Langton</hi> was an ill man, why was the Pope ſo importunate to haue him Arch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byſhop; &amp; if he were a good man, why did that Pope ſhortly after himſelfe excommunicate him? what bare rule here but fleſh &amp; bloud? Did <hi>Langton</hi> ſo farre paſſe <hi>Norwich</hi> that hee would do more good to the Church of England, then <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> could do if he were placed Archbiſhoppe; then the cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of all publicke ſeruice of God, &amp; adminiſtration of the ſacred Sacraments, for the ſpace of ſix years; (for ſo long the interdict laſteth) thoughout the whole land could do harme? how many ſoules may a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> probably think were loſt through this long irreligiouſnes which otherwiſe might haue bene ſaued<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I omit the great murdering of prieſts, the baniſhing of Byſhoppes, the raſing of Abbes, Churches &amp; Chappels, the manifould miſeries maſſacres &amp; waſts, that I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this more wilful or wofull interdict brought vnto this whol land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But ye wil ſay that before the land was interdicted the king had driuen out of the land the monks of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; ſeaſed on al their land, &amp; goods. And afterward did the like to the Byſhops that publiſhed the interdict. And alſo tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of al<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuch of the religious &amp; ſpiritual perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as did fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the Popes procedings; &amp; all this before he was depoſed by the Pope. But yet all theſe miſchieues proceeded of the Popes indirect dealing, to make his Cardinall Archbyſhop, and if the Pope woulde haue relinquiſhed that action, the king had ſoon bene appeaſed. And can any indifferent man thing that the king had not iuſt cauſe, to bee diſpleaſed with the Couent of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2432:27"/> who firſt choſe ſcecretly in the night, without his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedelier) there Superior Archbiſhoppe and alſo priuilye ſent him to Rome without the kings notice, to be confirmed of the Pope; and then miſliking of their owne doings elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Kings licence his fauourite Norwich, whom they afterward reiected, &amp; without the kinges licence choſe at Rome Langton, one whom the King knew not; And did not the Pope offer the King ſuch a wrong, as hath bene done neuer before, nor ſince that time to cauſe the couent to chooſe a Byſhoppe without the Kinges congedelier, &amp; that to at Rome by a few of the couent ſent thither in meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges without their Pryor. And if ye doe thinke the king dealt rigourouſly in baniſhing the Byſhoppes that interdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the land, and in ceaſing on their goodes that fauoured the Popes actions. How can you excuſe the Popes cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in interdicting the whole land, whereof one halfe did take his part. And faine would I know of you whether it proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of charitie that the Pope woulde not releaſe his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict and cenſures when the King offred to receiue <hi>Langton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew of Paris.</note> reſtore the baniſhed men, and fully to ſatiſfy all men for theire loſſes, vnleſſe he would alſo become his vaſſall, and make his realmes of England and Ireland tributarie for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnto the ſee of Rome; was this charitie, or couetouſnes and ambition. And againe came this of Charitie that the Pope, who ſtoode ſo ſtiffe for the reſtitution of the loſſes of the clergie, before the king had ſubiected himſelfe and his Realmes vnto him, did after that his owne turne was ſerued, force the Byſhoppes to take halfe their due, and the reſt of the clergie to beare their owne damages without one penny of recompence; And yet ſee more partialitie in this Pope. Firſt he excommunicated &amp; depoſed the king, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe he would not accept at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement <hi>Langton,</hi> for Archbiſhoppe; &amp; anone after exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated <hi>Langton</hi> and the Byſhoppes, and the Barrons his confederates; becauſe they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2432:27"/> woulde force the King to performe the oath which his owne legate had commaunded the King to ſweare, at the attonement making for the reſtoring of the auncient lawes of the land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if the lawes were vniuſt and it was a wronge to conſtraiee the King to reſtore them; why did hee force the King to ſweare the reſtitution of them. But if they weare iuſt, good, and godly, and for the publicke pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitte why did he not rather aſſiſt then excommunicate them that ſought to force the king to keepe his bodily oath, made vnto him and them, the which he had alſo done at his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation, yea, and had made (at the time of the peace with the Pope) a Charter of them which alſo this Pope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe confirmed. Now the caſe was altered (Although indeede this caſe was of greater moment) and the Pope muſt ſtill pleaſure his friendes. Firſt his cardinall was to be aduaunced to an Archbyſhoppricke, and then the king his new vaſſall was to be enfranchiſed of all othes and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, and vpholden and maintained with both ſworde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in all tyranny and villanie. If any credit is to bee giuen to all the Catholicke Cronicles of that age, And this I ſpeake not for that I doe like or allow the rebellion of the Barons,<note place="margin">Lib. 9.</note> but to ſhew the irreligious pertiality of the vniuſt, peruerſe paſſionate Pope. I doe alſo finde in <hi>Cromerus</hi> that the Archbyſhoppe of <hi>Gneſne</hi> did excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate <hi>Boleſlaw</hi> the balde one of the <hi>Polonian</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Duke of <hi>Legnitz</hi> for taking priſoner the byſhoppe of <hi>Preſlen</hi> and certain other of that Church and detaining them in priſon: And when that for all this he woulde not releaſe them without ranſome, Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the fourth willed the Archbyſhoppe to proclame a Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt him in <hi>Polen,</hi> and the Archbyſhoppe of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburge</hi> annother in <hi>Germany.</hi> But theſe excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for impriſoning of Prelates to proceede of partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie is manifeſtly diſcouered by the ſame <hi>Cromerus</hi> who
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2432:28"/> writes, that not farre from the ſame time another Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſhoppe of <hi>Gneſne,</hi> did excommunicate <hi>Boleſlawe</hi> the chaſt duke of the leſſer <hi>Polen,</hi> and interdicted the whole prouince becauſe certaine young Gentlemen had eyther by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion or permiſſion of <hi>Boleſlaw</hi> the chaſt, taken and kept one moneth in honorable cuſtodie <hi>Paule</hi> the Byſhoppe of <hi>Crac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow,</hi> becauſe that contrary to his calling, he was wholly giuen to pleaſures hunting and letchery, was grieuous to his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, ſtubburne towardes his Prince, neither would mende his manners for the entreatie &amp; admoniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Prince; but alſo tooke a Nunne out of a Nunery &amp; kept hir for his Concubine, Yet was the Godly Prince for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to let looſe this vngodly prelate &amp; to giue him two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounde of ſiluer for a mendes; whereas if he had giuen him his deſert, a halter, he had preuented a daungerous and bloodie Rebellion afterwarde in reuenge hereof pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by the Biſhoppe, alſo a pitifull waſting of the country done by the <hi>Lythuanians</hi> at his traiterous inſtigation. Hitherto ye haue heard not of one Prince depoſed for Chriſtes and the common cauſes, but all for priuate quarels, (here I willingly and wittingly omitte the depriuations of <hi>Sicilian</hi> and <hi>Neapolitaine</hi> Princes, and all other ouer whom the See of Rome clameth to haue Soueraignetie ſecular) And I can finde onely foure Princes depoſed for Religion. The firſt Raimond Earle of <hi>Tolowſen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Since the writing of this booke Henry king of Nauarre hath been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>priued of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by the P <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whether becauſe he did embrace the Religion of the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> or becauſe he did not expell them out of his dominions of certainety I know not. The ſeconde <hi>George Pogrebrot</hi> the King of <hi>Boemia,</hi> for maintaining the doctrine reuiued by <hi>Iohn Hus:</hi> And the third and fourth <hi>Henry</hi> the eight and his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> our renowned Princes and dreade Soueraignes. And although ſome hott headed Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes Romaine will perhappes praiſe the Popes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> zeale in depoſing of our Princes, yet muſt they needes all confeſſe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2432:28"/> that it was done ſmally for the weale of him, &amp; his friendes here, and therefore done without iudgement and diſcretion. And that theſe ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>do bulles haue killed many, and hurt more of the Popes friendes and fauourers, but not done one halfe penny worth of harme vnto them againſt whome they were ſent. And how ſmally they haue bene regarded of the Popes moſt deuouteſt children, it may apparantly appeare by the leagues made by <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour, and <hi>Charles</hi> the french King, with King <hi>Henry</hi> and her maieſty after they were excommunicated and depriued by the Popes; and the one an euerlaſting league both offenſiue and defenſiue to the euerlaſting ſhame of ſuch ſubiectes as haue ſought to reuolt, or ſhall wickedly beare armes againſt the ſoueraigne in that vniuſt quarrell. But to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, if wee doe wiſely weigh the matter and carefully call to minde all the wofull warres and waſtes, maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres, miſeries and calamities that this practiſe of depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Princes hath wrought, wee ſhall finde that the Weſt Church hath beene more waſted and weaken<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thereby, and that it hath cauſed the murder of moe men then all the cruel perſecutions of the heathen &amp; heretickes, and all the bloodie ſwordes of the Turkes and Saracens. Thus hauing ſhewed that this depoſing of Princes, is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther authoriſed by the word of God, nor warranted by the practiſe of the Iewiſh nor Chriſtian Church, within one thouſand yeares after Chriſt, nor then deuiſed or ſince practiſed,<note place="margin">The Pope cannot releaſe ſubiectes of their aleagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</note> for the profitte and benefitte of the Chriſtian common weale: Let vs goe vnto our third pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the Pope cannot looſe ſubiects of their natural &amp; duetifull faith and obedience vnto their Princes. It is the common opinion of all diuines Catholicke Romaine, that the Pope can not diſpenſe in thoſe things which are ordained by God. But this obedience to princes to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by the law of god, it is moſt manifeſt by the places which we haue
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2432:29"/> afore alleaged out of the ſacred Scriptures, in the firſt propoſition. Wherefore as Chriſt ſaide of Marriage thoſe whom God hath ioyned togeather let noe man ſeparate, and doth pronounce him to be an adulterer that doth put away his wife, and marrieth annother, vnleſſe it be for forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, notwithſtanding that <hi>Moſes</hi> had for the hardneſſe of the <hi>Iewes</hi> harts, permitted them many other cauſes. So likewiſe may not the Pope ſeparate the ſubiectes marryed to their prince (for ſo they are ſolemnely by a ring in our lande) from the Prince for any other cauſes then ſuch as God hath ordained, and what ſubiecte ſoeuer ſhall for any cauſes put away his Prince and take annother com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth rebellion and treaſon. And as Chriſt did abrogate that permiſſion of <hi>Moſes;</hi> ſo likewiſe muſt that of the Popes be repealed, and ſo much the rather becauſe the Popes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions are not ſo well warranted, as were <hi>Moſes</hi> ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, who receiued them of the very mouth of God himſelfe. And if Chriſt ſaide he came into the world not to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtroy the law but to fulfill it, by what right can the Pope who deriueth his authoritie from Chriſt as his ſubſtitute and deputy in the earth, claime the authoritie to make that voide which God hath ordained. And faine would I know of you, what faultes you finde in the word of GOD that ſubiectes may reuolt from their Prince, and take them to another, And I am ſure you cannot name me one, for doubtleſſe there can be noe greater faultes in a Prince then Idolatry and tyranny, and yet wee haue expreſſe commaundementes of GOD from his owne mouth vnto the people of Iſraell, for to bee obedient vnto two notorious Idolaters and triumphes,<note place="margin">An obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie with the wicked a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> the one by the Prophet <hi>Ieremy. Chap.</hi> 27. that they ſhould ſerue <hi>Nabuchadoniſor;</hi> the other by Chriſt himſelf, that they ſhould pay tribute vnto <hi>Ceſar.</hi> But ye will ſay that Chriſt ſaide if thy brother will not heare the Church let him bee
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2432:29"/> vnto thee as an Ethnicke and Publicane or cuſtomer, and that we are commaunded by <hi>Paule</hi> not to keepe company with the wicken, and by Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> not to ſay good morrow to an heretike. And now I would fayne know of you howe the <hi>Iewes</hi> did ſhunne an Ethnike and a publicane, did they not pay tributes and cuſtomes vnto ethnike Emperours, did they they not ſerue them in warre? finally did they not doe all dueties of loyall ſubiectes? did they not alſo come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the publicans to pay their cuſtoms, and towlles although they were nor familiar with them, &amp; did vſually keepe them company? Againe when Sant <hi>Paule</hi> did charge the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> not to keepe company with a brother that was a whoorhunter or couetous, or an idolatour or euill tongued or a dunkard, or a violent taker away of other mens goods, and not to eate meate with any ſuch. Doe you thinke the wife that had an husband, the childe a father, the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a Lord or maſter, infected with any of theſe faultes, were thereby incontinently diſcharged of all duety towardes them? yea and bound in conſcience ſpeedily to runne away from them, and neuer to doe them more ſeruice, nor come at them. I am ſure ye will ſay no, for by the canon law they are bound to abide with them being excommunicated, for any other faulte then for hereſy; And that is a latter edition of the Popes, for there is no ſuch diſtinction to be found, in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of God, nor his Apoſtles. But all excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated and wicked perſons, are alike commaunded to be ſhunned, and no difference to be put betweene the Idolater, and the whooremonger, So then if Chriſt and his Apoſtles did not diſcharge the wife, the childe, or bondman of their dueties towardes the excommunicated, neyther did they alſo the ſubiectes of their alleageance to their prince: for they be as faſt tyed to their prince by a bond and lawe, which onely death can vndoe, as the wife is to hir husband, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2432:30"/> therefore included in this word <hi>(Lex)</hi> of the canonicall verſe that ſhewes who may communicate with excommunicated perſons;<note place="margin">Vtile lex humile res ignorata neceſſe.</note> and alſo aſwell vnder and ſubiected to their ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, as the childe vnto his father, and the bondman vnto his Lord and maſter; and ſo are compriſed alſo in the word (humile) of the ſame verſe. But let vs returne where we left. The Pope depoſed <hi>Boleſlaw</hi> the king of <hi>Polen</hi> for ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his rage <hi>Staniſlaw</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Craccow;</hi> yet when <hi>Saule</hi> had without cauſe vniuſtly and tyrannically ſlayne <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimelech</hi> the high prieſt, and all his whole houſe ſaue one, that fortunately eſcaped, yea prieſtes, in number foureſcore and ſeuen, all the men, women, little children, ſucking babes, oxen, aſſes, and ſheepe that were in the Citie of the prieſtes, called <hi>Nob:</hi> Yet <hi>Dauid</hi> whom God had annointed king, and <hi>Saul</hi> did cauſeleſſe cruelly perſecute from place to place, &amp; ſought by all meanes to bereaue of life, yet thought not himſelfe diſcharged of his allegeance by this deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble murder of the ſacred prieſtes of God; but when hee had him twiſe at aduantage, ſaued his life, and tolde <hi>Abiſri</hi> who deſired him to diſpatch the tyrante with one blowe, ſlewe him not, for who ſhall ſtretch foorth his hande againſt the annoynted of the Lorde, and ſhall be innocent. As ſure as the Lord liueth, vnleſſe the Lorde ſhall ſtrike him, or his day ſhall come, that he die or periſh in ſight, God neuer be mercifull vnto me, if I doe ſtretch forth mine hande againſt the annoynted of the Lorde. Yee ſee heere a playne aſſertion of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that ſubiectes are not releaſed of their alleageance if that their princes fall to vngodlineſſe and tyranny, much leſſe doth he allowe that euerie priuate man murder him ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, yea when a younge man brought <hi>Dauid</hi> newes of <hi>Saules</hi> death, and preſented him with <hi>Saules</hi> diademe and bracelette, <hi>Dauid</hi> put him to death becauſe he had tolde him, that at the Kinges great inſtance, and entreatie that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2432:30"/> he might not fall into the handes of his enemies, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uironed him rounde about, hee beeing no <hi>Iſraelite</hi> but an <hi>Amalachite,</hi> had killed him, ſaying, why didſt thou not feare to ſende thy hande, that thou mighteſt kill the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted of the Lorde. And againe the bloode be vpon thy heade, for thy mouth hath ſpoken againſt thee, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I haue ſlaine the annoynted of the Lord. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing <hi>Dauid</hi> doth allowe no cauſe of reuoulte, and doth thinke that the ſubiectes are looſed of their allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance by no fault and wickedneſſe of their prince; by what warrant of the worde can the Pope at his pleaſure releaſe ſubiectes of their alleageance? And whereas we reade in the 34 of <hi>Iob,</hi> that GOD doth make the hypocrite man to raigne for the ſinnes of the people, or as other tranſlate it, to afflict and plauge the people, what a malapart parte is it of the Pope, to pull the rodde out of Gods hande by violence, and to chaſe him away, whome God hath ſpecially ſente to chaſtice his people. Neyther haue I ſucked this ſentence out of mine owne fingers endes, but learned it of a learned greate Pope, <hi>Gregorie</hi> the greate, who interpreting in his moralles the late rehearſed place of <hi>Iob,</hi> and alleadging vnto it the thirteenth of <hi>Oſee,</hi> I will giue Kinges in my furie, hath theſe wordes. <hi>Quid ergo illos nobis praeſſe deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picimus, quorum ſuper nos regimina ex Domini furore ſuſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimus?</hi> Why then doe we deſpiſe them to be our princes, whoſe raignes, and gouermentes ouer vs wee haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from the wrath of GOD? So that the Pope may not diſplace the good princes, becauſe they are good princes, nor the euill, becauſe they are placed by GOD to puniſh his people. And if the <hi>Canoniſtes</hi> holde, that no man can iudge the Pope, becauſe he ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the chiefeſt chaire. Who then ſhall iudge the king who is ſaide in <hi>2. Paralip. 9.</hi> to be ordained of God
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2432:31"/> to ſet vpon his owne throne, and ſhall any mortall man be ſoe audacious to pull him out of it? And if that no man can excommunicate the Pope becauſe no man is his ſuperiour, neyther can any man depoſe a king be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man is his ſuperiour. But the obiection out of <hi>Ruffinus</hi> his contimation of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great ſaid vnto the Biſhoppes aſſembled in the counſell of <hi>Nice.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Place of Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> God hath conſtituted you prieſtes, and hath giuen you power to iudge alſo of vs, and therefore iuſtly are we iudged by you. But what is the vttermoſt that can be infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of theſe wordes then a ſpirituall iudgement, for ſeeing he maketh them iudges becauſe they are prieſtes, and not princes, how can it import any ſecular power? for the name of prieſt ſignifieth a man ſeperat from ſecular matters, and wholly dedicated to heauenly and diuine. So that to ſay that Biſhoppes in that they are prieſtes are iudges ouer Kinges and Emperours, in matters touching their crowne and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie; is or abſurde as if a man ſhould ſay, the Apoſtles had power to remitte and retaine ſinnes becauſe they were fiſhermen. But as the Biſhoppes ſhewed themſelues farre from claiming any ſuch authoritie, by exhibiting vp vnto him as their ſoueraigne and chiefe iudge billes of complaint one againſt another. So alſo did <hi>Conſtantine</hi> continually pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe among them, and vpon them his Empyre and ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntie. So at the counſell at <hi>Nice,</hi> when the definition of faith was preſented vnto him by the counſell, not the counſell, but he did ſet downe the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall puniſhment, to the infringers thereof, he proteſting that he would baniſh all men that would not obey and embrace it; And ſo immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after he baniſhed <hi>Arrius,</hi> and certaine Biſhoppes that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to ſubſcribe. And afterward as we reade in <hi>Socrates</hi> he made an edict that all bookes of <hi>Arrius</hi> his doctrine ſhould be burned, and who ſoeuer did conceale any, and not bring them forth to the fire, ſhould die therefore, we alſo
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2432:31"/> finde in <hi>Theodoretus,</hi> that he baniſhed <hi>Euſebius</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> and <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gonus</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Nice,</hi> becauſe they ſought to peruert to the <hi>Arianiſme</hi> certaine <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrines,</hi> and that he wrote thus to the Citizens of <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>media:</hi> If there ſhall be founde any among you, that ſhall audaciouſly praiſe and commend theſe peſtilent Biſhoppes their combes ſhall be ſoone cut, by the execution of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God, that is by me. So that the office of beeing Gods miniſter he kept ſtill after he became a Chrſtian; ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it fallen vnto the Church by his embracing of the faith (as <hi>Pighius</hi> ſaith.) And although he refuſed at the beginning of the counſell, to heare and determine the accuſations, that the Biſhoppes did put vp vnto him one againſt another, of humility and pollicie, becauſe he would not haue that time vnprofitablie ſpent about priuate quarels which had beene appoynted for the common cauſe of Chriſt and his Church; and therefore burnt all their billes of complaint, yet that he dealt with the correction and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of Biſhoppes, it is apparant, by that which I haue alreadie alledged, and is made much more manifeſt by that <hi>Theodoretus</hi> writeth, how the <hi>Arrians</hi> of <hi>Aegypt</hi> ſuborned by money certaine fellowes (becauſe if they had done it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, it would haue ſmelt) to accuſe <hi>Athanaſius</hi> vnto <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> that he had ſet certaine impoſitions in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and giuen the money thereof to one, for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to raiſe a commotion in the country, whereupon the Emperour ſent for him to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before him at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (a long iourney for the chiefe patriarch of the Eaſt,) whither he came and cleared himſelfe ſo ſubſtantially, that ſaies <hi>Tbeodoretus</hi> he recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe his Church allotted vnto him by God, which is as much to ſay, if he could not haue ſatisfied the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour he had loſt his Biſhoppricke. After this his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies accuſed him againe vnto Emperour of many greate crimes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who thereupon following the honorable cuſtome of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2432:32"/> this land that all men are tried by their peeres, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Biſhoppes of thoſe countries to aſſemble together in counſell at <hi>Ceſaria</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> to heare the matter of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> whither, when <hi>Athanaſius</hi> came not, becauſe he thought, that ſeeing moſt that were aſſembled were his enemies he ſhould finde no iuſtice there: then they hauing gotten more pretences of ſlaunder accuſed him vnto the Emperour of audaciouſneſſe and tyranny. See how it was accounted for an audacious part and rebellious, for a patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke not to appeare where the Emperour had commaunded him. Neyther did there hope deceiue them, for then the Emperour being exaſperated did in letters vnto <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> both declare his diſpleaſure and alſo commanded him to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare at <hi>Tyrus</hi> for there ſhould be held a counſell of Biſhops. <hi>Socrates</hi> reports that he threatned <hi>Athanaſius</hi> that if he would not goe of himſelfe, he ſhould be fet by force. He alſo wrote vnto the counſell at <hi>Tiru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> in which letters <hi>Theodoretus</hi> hath theſe wordes. I haue ſent vnto you <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> one that hath beene conſul, for to be preſident of the aſſembly, that if any man (which I thinke will not happen) now all little regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you commaundement ſhall not be there, that there may be one hence from vs, that by emperiall commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may baniſh him, and teach him (marke well theſe wordes) that he muſt not diſobey the order that the king hath appointed for the trying of a trueth; But when <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> who ſingularly well acquitted himſelfe coulde yet obtaine no iuſtice there, ſecretly fled vnto the Emperour to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and put vp an appeale vnto him, <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> thereupon commaunded all the Biſhoppes of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to appeare before him at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> with all ſpeede; the tenor of the mandate <hi>Socrotes</hi> ſetteth downe thus. That all ye that held the counſell at <hi>Tyrus</hi> to immediately haſten to appeare before vs, for to ſhew by deed the ſinceritie and vprightneſſe of your iudgement before me, that is to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2432:32"/> wit him whome not ye your ſelues ſhall deny to be the prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per miniſter of God. From what power came this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement to a counſell to appare before the Emperour, and to render a reaſon vnto him of their iudgement, as vnto the chiefe miniſter and officer of God. But to proceede with our hiſtorie: when the Biſhoppes were come to <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> they for feare of aſſured conuiction gaue ouer their olde ſlaunders, and charged <hi>Athanaſius</hi> with a newe lie, that he ſhould ſay vnto foure Biſhoppes, that he woulde let the comming of corne from <hi>Alexandria</hi> vnto <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the which the Emperour ouer lightly beleeuing, baniſhed <hi>Athanaſius</hi> into <hi>Trier</hi> in <hi>Germany<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> where was now the Pope to depoſe the Emperour for baniſhing wrongfully the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Patriarch of the Eaſt; this was worſe then the empri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning of the Biſhop of <hi>Apamea</hi> by the french king for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him ill languages. But to returne to our matter: <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> doth write that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his firſt troubles beganne, becauſe he woulde not receiue into the Church <hi>Arrius</hi> whome the Emperour did nowe take for a penitent and honeſt man, whereuppon hee thus wrote vnto <hi>Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi> Seeing that you doe nowe vnderſtande the tenor of the counſell and of my will, ſee that you doe giue all men entrance into the Church that are deſirous to come in, for if I ſhall vnderſtande, that any man that deſireth to be made partaker of the Church, ſhall eyther be let by you or forbidden to enter in, I will immediately ſende one of mine, that by my commaundement ſhall remooue you, from your Sea, and giue your place vnto another. Note that hee ſaieth I will ſende, not the Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome</hi> his officer; but one of mine owne men who ſhall diſplace you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and place another therein, not by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the counſell or Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome,</hi> but by my commaundement. The like alſo, writes <hi>Socrates,</hi> he threatned vnto <hi>Alexander</hi> the Biſhoppe of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:2432:33"/> if he woulde not receiue <hi>Arrius</hi> into the Church. But you will ſay that the Emperour iniuried both <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> I denie not that, but although <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doretus</hi> doth blame his ouermuch light credulitie, and doth excuſe it by the like in <hi>Dauid</hi> againſt <hi>Miphiboſeth,</hi> yet doth neyther hee nor any other ancient author ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him of tyranny, for medling with matters that he had nothing to do withall, or puniſhing of them ouer whom he had no lawfull iuriſdiction, and alſo doth refute that you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> refuſed to iudge Biſhoppes. Nowe to returne againe to the hiſtory, the ſame <hi>Socrates</hi> doth ſay that when the <hi>Arrians</hi> had accuſed <hi>Athanaſius, Maca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> and other of their complices vnto the Emperour of foule factes. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> wrote vnto his ſiſters ſonne <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linatius</hi> who was then abiding at <hi>Antioch</hi> 500 miles from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> to call the parties before him, and to puniſh them that he ſhoulde finde faultie. But afterwarde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Biſhoppes were aſſembled at <hi>Tyrus</hi> about the dedication of his newe Church at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> he referred ouer the hearing of thoſe matters vnto them. So that at the firſt he had committed both the triall, and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the greateſt Biſhoppe of all the Eaſt Church vnto a temporall officer of his; the which fact and the other which I haue before rehearſed, doe plainly proue that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> did not account, nor acknowledge his Empyre, or him ſelfe empaired, or of leſſe commaund by accepting of the Chriſtian religion, but that he ſtill executed his princely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue, on all perſons both ſpirituall &amp; temporall, and ſtill clamed to be the miniſter immediate of God, &amp; not any vnder officer of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> Gods vicar on earth, &amp; right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to, for as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>1. Tim. 6.</hi> Let all bondmen whatſoeuer they be that be vnder yoke, repute their lords worthy of al ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor, leſt the name of the lord &amp; his doctrine be blaſphemed, but they which haue beleeuing Lords, let them not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2432:33"/> them, becauſe they bee their brethren, but rather ſerue them becauſe they bee beleeuers, and belooued who are pertakers of the benefite Teach theſe thinges and exhort them: If any man teach otherwiſe and doth not yeeld vnto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound ſpeaches of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which is agreeable to godlineſſe, is proud know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing, is mindeſicke of queſtions &amp; quarrelles, about wordes. So alſo might it haue been ſaide: Ye Popes &amp; Byſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oppes account your princes worthie of all honour, leaſt the name and doctrine of Chriſt be euill ſpoken of, but ye Byſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oppes that haue Chriſtian Kinges contemne them not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be Chriſtians, but be the more obedient and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull vnto them, becauſe they haue embraced Chrſt, and are pertakers of his benefit. This teach and exhorte but whoſoeuer teacheth otherwiſe, teacheth contrary doctrine to Chriſt, is a proude prelate, and quite voide of knowledge And as <hi>Peter</hi> writeth 1 Epiſtle 3. Ye bondmen bee ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect in all feare vnto your Lordes not onely vnto them that are good and moderate, but alſo vnto them that are waywarde and vnreaſonable, for this is grace or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of fauour, if a man doe beare ſorrowes for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of GOD, ſuffering vniuſtly. So alſo might it haue beene rightly ſaide vnto the Popes and Byſhoppes in <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time, and now alſo: be ye ſubiecte in all feare vnto your Princes, not onely vnto ſuch as are good and gratious, but alſo vnto vngodly and tyrannicall, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther releaſe your ſelues of your alleagence, for if yee doe take and beare wrong quietly for regarde of GOD, God will abundadtly rewarde your patience; for the conſequent is very ſtrong and good, ſeeing the thinges are all together alike and equall; for if the Chriſtian bondmen were not enfranchiſed, becauſe they were ſpirituall brothers vnto their Lordes, neyther were the Popes and Byſhoppes diſcharged of ſubiection vnto their Princes, becauſe they
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2432:34"/> were become their ſpirituall bretheren, and if you will to, their ſpirituall fathers. But they ſay with <hi>Phig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius</hi> that Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted the gouernement of his Church vnto <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">What prince Peter was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> and his ſucceſſors, and therefore all Kinges that are of the Church are ſubiect vnto the Byſhoppes of Rome. And if we grant, this can there bee ought elſe inferred then ſubiection in cauſes and cenſures eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, and not in cauſes and puniſhmentes ſecular and temporall: for what fonde Frenchman will ſay that becauſe in olde time the Kinges of England were vaſſals vnto the French Kinges, for the Duchies of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> and <hi>Guien,</hi> that therefore the crowne of Englande was ſubiect vnto the Kinges of France, or that they coulde commande the Kinges of England in any matter touching their crowne of England: or becauſe the Byſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oppes Chanceller can excommunicate a man for adultery, that therefore he can alſo depriue a man of life and liuing,<note place="margin">Mat. 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> for a greater fault. Moreouer did not Chriſt plainelye enough declare what kinde of Kingdome he gaue to <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, and how vnkingely kinges they ſhoulde bee; when they contended among themſelues who ſhould be greateſt. The kinges of nations (ſaide he) be Lordes ouer thoſe countries, and their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer haue power ouer them, but ſo it is not in you: doth he not here in plaine wordes take from them all earthlye and bodily Empire and power, and that too from the greateſt of them; So that the Pope that claimeth to bee greateſt and chiefeſt, is alſo hereby excluded: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will a ſhifte of humilitie ſerue to eſcape, ſeeing that to depoſe Princes is to raigne ouer nations, is to be their Lord, is to haue power ouer them, all which thinges Chriſt ſaith the greateſt of his Apoſtles, &amp; his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors ſhould not haue: nor conſequently authoritie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe all ſubiectes of their allegiance the which is a ſupreeme
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2432:34"/> point of Earthly Empire, the which neuer any mortall man yet had and onely belongeth vnto the great God, the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preeme Lord and ſoueraigne of the whole world; for neuer yet was there any ſo mightie a monarch, that had all the world vnder his Empire, neither then could his authoritie extend ouer all nations: but his power determined within the bonds of his owne Empire, &amp; could not ſtretch beyonde his owne vaſſals, among whom only he might decree in what caſes their ſeignories ſhould be forfeated, and their bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men be enfranchiſed of the ſeruice of their Lordes and not preſcribe lawes therein vnto all other not ſubiect vnto him, no more then the Queene of England can enacte, that if the king of Spaine ſhall doe this and this, that then hee ſhall forfeite his Crowne,<note place="margin">Noe law of the Church touching tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lties euer alowed in this Realme</note> or the king of France make an edict that if any Lord in England ſhal committe ſuch and ſuch faultes, that then he ſhall forfitte all his propertie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his bondmen, and they to be enfranchiſed. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe the Princes of this Realme did neuer ackno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge themſelues vaſſals vnto the Pope, nor the See of Rome, nor neuer agniſed him for their Soueraigne in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralities, they did neuer heare when the Popes authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was greateſt, adminiſter iuſtice and adiudge ſecular cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes here. according to the Popes decrees, and Canons of the counſels, but alwaies according to the lawes coſtomes and ſtatutes of the Realme, and in thoſe cauſes the Canon law had no authoritie, and force in this Land. This is ſo often affirmed by the author of the learned booke called the Doctor and ſtudent, (who as he was a greate lawyer, ſo was he alſo a good diuine and deuout Catholicke) that it weare tedious to rehearſe them all. In the xliiii. Chapter of thee ſeconde booke thus hee writeth: for the ordinarie, no yet the partie himſelfe haue any authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to binde any inheritance by the authoritie of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall law, how then can they binde the inheritance of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2432:35"/> the crowne, And againe in the ſame Chapter, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſomwhat to bee meruelled that ordinaries will admitte ſuch land for a title &amp;c. without knowing how the common law will ſerue therein, for of meere right all inheritance within this Realme ought to bee ordered by the Kinges Law. Alſo in the xxxvi. Chapter of the ſecond booke, the Doctor of diuinitie ſaith, yet me thinkes alwaies that the title of the lapſe, in ſuch caſe is giuen by the law of the Church, and not by the temporall law, and therefore it forceth but little what the temporall law will in it as me ſeemeth. Whereunto the author anſwereth thus vnder the name of the ſtudent of law. In ſuch cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries where the Pope hath power to determine the right of temporall thinges I thinke it is as thou ſayeſt, but in this realme it is not ſo. And the right of preſentment is a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall thing; and a temporall inheritance, and therefore I doe thinke it belongeth to the Kinges law to determine, and alſo to make lawes who ſhall preſent after the ſix mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, aſwell as before, ſo that the title of abilitie, or none abilitie, be not therefore taken from the ordinaries. And in like wiſe it is of auoidance of benefices, that is to ſay that it ſhall be iudged by the Kinges lawes, when a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice ſhalbe ſaide uoide and when not, and not by the law of the Church, and ſhall the law of the Church determine when the crowne is voide? As when a parſon is made a Byſhoppe, or accepteth another benefice without licence or reſigneth, or is depriued, in theſe cauſes the common law ſaith, that the benefices be voide, And ſo they ſhould be though the Church had made a law to the contrarie. And ſo if the Pope ſhould haue any title in this caſe to preſent, it ſhould be by the lawe of this Realme. And if hee ſhould haue title to preſent vnto the Crowne ſhould it not bee by the lawe of this Realme? And I haue not ſeene ne harde that the lawes of this Realme
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2432:35"/> haue giuen any title to the Pope to determine any temporal thing that may be lawfully determined by the Kings Court, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that he may depoſe the King, and giue his kingdom vnto any forreiner, but becauſe noe man ſhould repute this lawyer for a Lollard and enimie vnto the Pope, ſee what immediately followeth. Doctor. It ſeemeth by the reaſon that thou haſt made now, that thou preferreſt the Kinges authoritie in preſentments, before the Popes, and that me thinkes ſhould not ſtand with the Law of God, ſyth the Pope is the vicar generall vnder GOD. Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, That I haue ſaide prooueth nor, for the higheſt preferment in preſentmentes, is to haue authoritie to examine the abilitie of the perſon that is preſented, for if the preſented bee able, it ſufficeth to the diſcharge of the ordinary by whomeſoeuer hee bee preſented; &amp; that authoritie is not denyed by the lawe of the Realme to belong alwaies to the ſpirituall iuriſdiction. Thus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the authour, of the Doctor and the ſtudent (whom ſome ſuppoſe to be Sainte <hi>Germany</hi>) is prooued to bee noe partiall man againſt the Pope, but onely a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Lawyer that ſetteth downe vprightly, to the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of mens conſciences, what right euery man hath, and declareth the common opinion of his time when the Popes power was in the Prime: we will rehearſe yet more out of him to the confirmation of you, our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke countrimen who doe openly profeſſe, that ye will grant her maieſtie as much, and as greate authoritie, as any of her anceſtors before hir father had, ſince the conqueſt yea or ſince they embraced the faith of Chriſt. In the xlvii Chapter of the ſeconde booke, he ſaith that although by the Canon Law the Pope ought to preſent to all bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or dignities, the incumbents whereof dye at Rome or within two dayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourney thereof, yet he ſaith that it hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this Realme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe by the lawes of this
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2432:36"/> realme the King ought according to the auncient right of his crowne, to preſent of all his aduowſons that be of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage. And in likewiſe other patrons of benefices of their preſentment, and the plea of the right of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments of benefice is within this Realme belongeth to the King and his Crowne. And theſe titles can not be taken from the king and his ſubiectes but by their aſſent, and ſo the law that is made therein to put away that title bindeth not in this realme. Then may I reaſon of a ſtronger, that the Kinges title to the Crowne can not be taken away without his conſent, and ſo the Law that is made therin by the Church to put away that title, bindeth not in this Realme. But to returne againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to preſentments of benefices, who knoweth not the terrible ſtatute of premunire, made in the Raigne of <hi>Edwarde</hi> the third, againſt all ſuch as ſhoulde prouide Engliſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices or ſpirituall dignities from Rome, or purchaſe them from the Pope, and alſo againſt all atturneyes, and agents in that matter, againſt the which ſtatute the Pope neuer ſpurned but ſuffered it (ſaith Saint <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi>) and it hath alwaies beene vſed in this Realme with-without reſiſtance, yea and in the ſtatute made againſt the prouiſions and tranſlations of Byſhoppes by the Pope made in the xvi. yeare of the raigne of <hi>Richarde</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond the vi. Chapter, we finde in thoſe wordes the cauſe of the making of the ſtatute, leaſt the Crowne of this realme which is immediatly ſubiect to God, and to none other in al thinges touching the royaltie of the ſame Crowne, ſhoulde be ſubmitted to the ſea of Rome. We doe alſo reade there, that all the Barons, and all the Byſhoppes preſent, and the deputies of thoſe which were abſent, being aſked euery man ſeuerally ſaide that therein they would to their vttermoſt ſtand with the King againſt the Pope ſo zealous were all good Engliſhmen in thoſe daies of the auncient ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2432:36"/> and libertie of their country, and the ſoueraignetie of their King. Moreouer Saint <hi>Germanye</hi> in the xxxix. Chapter of the ſecond booke, entreating how eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call perſons may diſpoſe of their goodes, he vtterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecteth the Canon law therein, and ſheweth what they may doe by the lawes of this Realme, and at the length he ſaith thus, And moreouer a parſon of a Church vicar &amp; Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery prieſt, or ſuch other; all ſuch goods as they haue by reaſon of the parſonage vicarage or Chauntery, as that they haue by reaſon of their owne perſon, they may lawfully giue and bequeth after the common law, And if they diſpoſe part among their pariſhoners, and part to the building of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or giue part to the ordinary, or to poore men, or in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch manner as is appoynted by the law of the Church, they offend not therein; vnleſſe they thinke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues bound thereunto by duety, &amp; authoritie of the law of the Church, not regarding the Kings lawes. For if they doe ſo it ſeemeth they reſiſt the ordinance of God, which hath giuen power to princes to make lawes. But whereas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Pope hath ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignety in temporall things, as he hath in ſpirituall thinges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there ſome ſay that the goods of prieſts muſt in conſcience be diſpoſed, as it is contained in the ſame ſumme. But it holdeth not in this Realme, for the goodes of ſpirituall men, bee temporall in what manner ſoeuer they come to them, and muſt be ordered by the temporall law as the goodes of temporall men muſt be. Thus farre Sainte <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many;</hi> then may I inferre: if that the Pope, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and thee conuocation can not make a Lawe touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the goodes of the ſpirituallty within this Realme, and that thoſe which doe diſpoſe of their goodes according to ſuch a Canon doe ſinne, although it doe agree with the law of this Realme, if they did it as bounde by that Canon: ſhall wee thinke that the Pope, the councell, or the conuocation can giue away the goodes, and landes
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2432:37"/> of temporall men within this Realme, yea and the Crowne and kingdome, and that they doe not ſinne mortally that doe obey any ſuch decrees? And what account is to bee made of the Popes diſpenſation in temporall cauſes, the ſame learned author plainely declareth in the xli. Chapter of the ſeconde booke where hee ſaith, That although by the Canon law euery man may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kill an Aſſaſin (ſuch a fellow as will at euery mans requeſt kill any man for money) yet he affirmeth it is altogether vnlawfull in this land; and that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Popes diſpenſation and pardon, he that ſlayeth an Aſſaſin is a fellon, and ſo ought to bee puniſhed as a fellon. Moreouer in his xliiii. Chapter hee doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantly holde, that the Canon ſummes that do determine all ſcruples of conſcience according to the Canon law doe rather hurt Engliſh mens conſciences, then giue them light, and that there bee many caſes in them ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led according to the Canon law that are not to bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in this Realme, neyther in law nor conſcience. And in xlii. Chapter that although many ſayings in the ſame ſummes doe agree with the lawes of this Realme, yet they are to be obſerued by the authoritie of the Lawes of this Realme, and not by the authoritie alleaged by them. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in the xxix. Chapter of the ſame booke hee doth flatly ouerrule our preſent caſe, whereas by the Canon Law an heretike hath <hi>ipſo facto</hi> loſt all his goodes, and therefore can make noe execution, he affirmeth that it holdeth and bindeth not here, for if he doe abiure hee hath forfeited noe goods, but if hee be conuicted of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie and deliuered to laye mens handes he hath forfey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all his goodes, that he hath at that time, that he was deliuered vnto them; but not his landes, before that he be put to death. To this the Doctor anſwereth: me thinketh that as it onely belongeth vnto the Church to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2432:37"/> hereſies that ſo it belongeth vnto the Church what puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he ſhal haue for his hereſie, except, death which they can not be iudges in; but if the Church decree that therfore he ſhall forfeite his goods, me thinkes that they be forfeyted by that decree; vnto this obiection he thus anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnder the name of ſtudent. Nay verely for they be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things, and belong to the iudgement of the kings court; And I thinke that the ordinarie might haue ſet no fine vpon one impeached of hereſie, vntill it was ordained by the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, that he may ſet a fine if hee ſee cauſe, and that the king ſhall haue that fine. If this were the vniuerſall beliefe of all good Engliſhmen in the time, when the Popes authoritie moſt flouriſhed heere, and before this controuerſie aroſe; that neither the Pope, nor counſell, nor Church, hath authoritie to ordaine any temporall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for hereſy, can he be accounted a true Engliſhman that doth holde that the Pope can depriue her maieſtie of her crowne and dignitie for a pretence of hereſy?<note place="margin">Of the counſell of Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rane.</note> or that the Canon made in the counſell held at <hi>Laterane</hi> doth binde vs heere in England? But becauſe we vnderſtand that the greateſt ſcruple in conſcience of our Catholickes Romane is grounded vpon this Canon: we will make a particular treatiſe thereof, and to vncomber and diſcharge their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſhew firſt that it is no determination of faith that the Pope may depoſe princes, and ſecondly that it doth not binde in this realme, not onely becauſe as I haue proued before, the Church can make no decree of temporalities, but alſo becauſe by the verie Canon Lawe, it neither is, nor euer was in force within this realme; and finally neither orderly executed according to the order of the Canon. And firſt becauſe I ſhall haue occaſion to examine euerie worde of one member thereof I will ſet it downe <hi>verbatim</hi> worde for worde. <hi>Ca. 33<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Si ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dominus temporalis requiſitus &amp; admonitus ab eccleſia, terram ſuam purgare neglexerit ab hac
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2432:38"/> haeretica foeditate, per Metropolitanum &amp; comprouinciales epiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos, excommunicationis vinculo innodetur, etſi ſatisfacer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> contempſerit intra annum, ſignificetur hoc ſummo pontifici Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. vt extunc ipſe, vaſallos ab eius fidelitate denuntiet abſolutos &amp; terram exponat Catholicis occupandam, qui cam exterminatis hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticis ſine contradictone posſideant, &amp; in fidei puritate conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent: ita quod bona huiuſmodi damnatorum, ſi laici fuerint, confiſcentur, ſi vero clereci applicentur eccleſijs a quibus ſtipendia per ceperint.</hi> Which may thus be engliſhed, If the temporall Lord beeing requeſted and admoniſhed by the Church, ſhall neglect to purge his land from this hereticall filthineſſe, let him be inknotted with the band of excommunication, by the Metropolitane and Biſhoppes of that prouince: And if he ſhall contemne to ſatisfie within one yeare, let this be ſignified vnto the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> that he may denounce his vaſſalles acquitted of his fealtie, and expone or ſet forth, his land vnto the Catholikes for them to take, who, the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes being driuen out may poſſeſſe it without contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and keepe it in the puritie of the faith: ſo that the goods of ſuch condemned men, if they be laye men, be eſcheted to the prince, or if they be clarkes, be applied to the Churches of whom they receiued ſtipendes; Heere ye ſee is no defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſentence of faith ſet downe, but onely an order appointed to be vſed for the rooting out of hereſies, ſo that no weake Catholike conſcience neede to make ſcruple, that the Pope can depoſe princes becauſe the counſel doth ſay let it ſignified to the Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome,</hi> that he may denounce his ſubiectes looſed of their obedience, &amp;c. For the counſell goeth no more about to decide whether Biſhoppes of <hi>Rome</hi> may depoſe princes, then whether Biſhoppes may excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate them, whereof no man in thoſe daies doubted, but content themſelues with the vſed and practiſed authority of them both, for long before this time had the Popes vſed to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2432:38"/> depoſe princes, as Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth, the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Boleſlaw</hi> king of <hi>Poland.</hi> And <hi>Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius tertius</hi> the preſent Pope that then held the counſell, had himſelfe before that time depoſed the Emperours <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Otho, Iohn</hi> the king of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Raymond</hi> the Earle of <hi>Tolouſe.</hi> So that ſeeing no man did then moue any doubt, whether Popes might lawfully doe it or no, neither did the counſell then goe about to determine it, but wholly omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the matter, doth onely ſet downe an order to be vſed for the deſtroying of hereſies. But otherwiſe if ye ſhoulde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies inferre, that for decreed for faith and lawfull, which generall counſels doe manie times as it were ſecretly receiue and not reproue; ye will neuer be able to defend them from errour in faith, and that which is equiualent, from beeing one, contradictorie vnto another; For at the ſecond coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Nice</hi> it is not refuted,<note place="margin">Cap. 32.</note> but rather it ſeemeth by the way to be allowed, that Angels haue materiall bodies. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe this counſell may after a ſort ſeeme to allowe, that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons may lawfully in good conſcience detayne, a greate parte of the tythes and profits of their Churches, ſo that they doe leaue the vicar a ſufficient liuing: becauſe that this counſell finding faulte with this miſorder, that patrons and certaine other perſons doe take the profits of the pariſh Churches, doth charge them with no more: then the which what can be more againſt good conſcience and equity, then he to liue by the altar that ſerueth not at the altar; and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among Catholickes Romane that doe holde, that tythes are by the lawe of God due onely to prieſtes, and with what conſcince then can any lay man enioy them. Likewiſe in the ſame counſell there is a Canon, that he that hath a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church ſhall not ſerue the cure by his vicar, but by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnleſſe perhaps the Church be annexed to a prebende or dignitie, in the which caſe we do grant that he which hath a prebend or dignitie, ſeeing it muſt be, that he do ſerue in the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2432:39"/> greater Church, that he doe endeuour to haue in that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church a meete and perpetuall vicar canonically inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, &amp;c. Heere ye ſee that this counſell doth not thinke that reſidence vpon benefices with charge of ſoules is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by God his lawe; which is contrary to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell at <hi>Treent</hi> in the 23 <hi>Section</hi> in the firſt chapter of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. Yea <hi>Dominicus Soto</hi> in his booke <hi>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertitudine gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae</hi> againſt <hi>Catherine,</hi> doth flatly affirme, that all the Biſhops &amp; learned men that were at that counſell did ſo wholly agree thar reſidence was required by the lawe of God, that there was not one man that doubted thereof but onely <hi>Catherine.</hi> Moreouer this counſell thinkes it meeter that a man be reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the Cathedrall Church, then in his pariſh Church, yea it ſeemeth to ſay of duetie it muſt be ſo, a thing verie abſurd in <hi>Dominicke Soto</hi> his iudgement; who ſharply repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the Cardinalles that haue Biſhopprickes, and be not reſident on them, but abide and continue at <hi>Rome;</hi> and thinketh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it no reaſon that they alleage that they ought to make their abode at <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe they be Cardinalles, and as it were aſſiſtants vnto the Pope, for ſaith he, reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences vpon Biſhopprickes are commaunded by God, but Cardinalles to be attendant on the Pope is but a conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man, the which muſt needes giue place to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances more ancient and greater. And bitterly doth he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey againſt the common abuſe: that whereas by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Church no Cardinall may be a Biſhoppe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe both offices require reſidence, which one man can not performe, the Cardinalles to delude the force of this Canon, are neuer inſtituted Biſhoppes but haue Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopprickes giuen them in perpetuall <hi>commenda,</hi> whereby it is come to paſſe that the ordinance of <hi>Commendaes</hi> which was firſt inſtituted for the benefite of the Church by ſuffering one to haue the gouernment of it, for a time vntill a meete man might be founde for it; is nowe vſed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2432:39"/> to the deſtruction of the Church, and the vnlawfull enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the couetous &amp; ambitious. Yea the counſell of <hi>Trent</hi> in the 25. <hi>Section. Chap.</hi> 18. doth thinke this Canon of the counſell of <hi>Laterane,</hi> ſo vnreaſonable and vniuſt, for to impropriate benefices with charge of ſoules; and to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine in them a perpetuall vicar, to ſerue the cure; that they doe forbid the like to be done euer hereafter notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any grace or grant: wiſely weying the difference betweene an inſtitution of God, and an ordinance of man, the ſeruing of God in a publike charge &amp; in priuate perſon, &amp; finally howe much greater good or hurt may enſue by the continuall preſence, or the abſence of the perſon in, or from his pariſh, then by his lying at, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Cathedral Church. Soe that to ſalue all this gere, both ye and we are forced to ſay, that the counſels went not about to determine what ought to be beleeued in thoſe poyntes, and ſo alſo muſt ye doe in this controuerſie of depoſing princes, and not to account it for a definition of faith, but a politique conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Of which kinde of Canons Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">De Baptiſ-Donat: lib. 2. cap 3.</note> who knoweth not, that former generall counſels are often amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the latter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when by ſome experiment of thinges, that is opened which had beene ſhut, and that knowen that lay hidden, without any type of ſacrilegious pride, without any ſwollen necke of vaine glorie, without any contention of ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>full enuie, with holy humilitie, Catholike peace, and Chriſtian charitie. Moreouer the famous Cardinall <hi>Taie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that doth hold and maintaine that the Pope cannot erre in the definition of faith, yet doth affirme in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries vpon <hi>Mathew</hi> that he may erre in iudgement, whether a thing be lawfull or noe: And therefore he doth not accept the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rees of the Pope, in his controuerſie of diuotee for definitiue of faith, but for iudiciall: And in iudgementes the Popes themſelues (ſaith he) doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2432:40"/> that they haue erred; and ſo then may alſo a generall counſell erre in iudgements by your owne rules, if perhaps any iudgement be to be founde of the counſell of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane, againſt <hi>Raimond</hi> the Earle of <hi>Tolouſe,</hi> for not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his country of the <hi>Albigenſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Canons of counſels binde not but where they are receiued.</note> Nowe this firſt ſcruple beeing taken away, let vs deſcend vnto our next article and concluſion, that the Canon doth not binde vs in this realme; who is ſo ignorant that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that all decrees and Canons of generall counſels, are not obſerued and kept in euerie country, neyther doe thy binde the breakers of them in conſcience; As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, there was a decree made by the counſell at <hi>Nice,</hi> that deacons ſhall not ſit aboue prieſtes: but yet we doe ſee at <hi>Rome,</hi> the Deacon Cardinalles, doe ſitte aboue Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes that be no Cardinalles. Likewiſe in <hi>Sexto Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinapolitano in Trullo,</hi> there is forbidden kneeling in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er on the Sundayes, and ſoe likewiſe all the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Eaſter and Whitſontide, And alſo that no man ſhall faſt the Saturnedaies in Lent: but the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie of both Canons, was moſt vſuall in this lande, and thought moſt deuoute when the Pope was in his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt prime heere. Moreouer it is the common opinion of all the <hi>Canoniſtes,</hi> that the decrees and Canons refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue doe not elſe where binde, but where they haue beene receiued, and therefore our ſeminary prieſtes doe holde, that the Catholickes Romane of this Realme, nor yet thoſe in <hi>France,</hi> be not bounde to obſerue the Canons of the late counſell at <hi>Trent,</hi> becauſe they haue beene publikly receiued in neyther of the kingdomes. This then beeing ſoe, if I can prooue that this Canon of depoſing of princes was neuer receiued in this Realme, then haue I conuinced that it doth binde no man of this Realme in conſcience. And this will I firſt prooue by cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2432:40"/> of the time, and ſecondly, becauſe diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for downe in the ſame counſell were neuer obſerued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, as for this Canon,<note place="margin">The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non neuer receiued, proued by circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time.</note> it neuer came in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe heare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntill Kinge <hi>Henrie</hi> the eyght. Firſt it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that the counſell at <hi>Laterane</hi> was helde in <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> 1215. and in the ſeuenth yeare of the raigne of Kinge <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> and in the time of the bloodie broyles of the Barons, againſt the kinge, it can not bee denyed but that the kinge had three Embaſſadours there, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie enough it is, that they ſubſcribed and conſented as the reſt of the Embaſſadours did, for their maſter ſought all the meanes he coulde to pleaſe the Pope; that hee might haue his helpe againſt the Barons; and ſo indeede hee ſtoode his faſt friende, and at the counſell, accurſed the Barons, ſuſpended the Archbiſhoppe of <hi>Canterburie Stephan Lang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> for taking parte with them, and for the ſame quarrell would not allowe his brother <hi>Simon</hi> Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Archbiſhoppe of yorke, ſo that there is no doubte but the greateſt parte of the realme, were as readie to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe the Pope, as their prince was to pleaſe him, for the chiefeſt cauſe that moued the king to ſende Embaſſadours vnto the counſell was, ſaith <hi>Mathews</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> to procure the Popes curſe againſt the Barons. Theſe wofull warres continued to the death of kinge <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſoe that no parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was, or coulde be helde, whereby this Canon could be receiued: For if Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> in his debellation doth truely ſay, that kinge <hi>Iohn</hi> coulde not make his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome tributarie to the Pope, without the conſente of the parliament, much leſſe coulde he giue the Pope authority to giue the realme away, God knowes to whom it ſhould pleaſe him, or that Chriſtian that was able to winne it by fine force, for according to the rule of the Canon Lawe, <hi>Quod omnes tangit ab omnibus debet approbari,</hi> that which touch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2432:41"/> all men ought to be allowed and approued and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by all, wherefore the Lord chiefe Iuſtice in the firſt yeare of the raigne of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth, as we doo reade in the reportes of the ſame yeare <hi>Termino Hillarii. Chap.</hi> 10. affirmed, that all the Barrons vnto the Pope that after a ſorte commaunded <hi>Edwarde</hi> the firſt to ſurceaſe from warring on the Scottes that helde of him: That although the king woulde giue away the right he had to <hi>Scotlands,</hi> yet for all that it ſhoulde not be ſoe, becauſe that hee that is king of <hi>England</hi> is alwaies chiefe Lorde of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And if the king of this Realme, cannot of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe diſpoſe of a thing annexed and incorporated to the crowne of this kingdome: will any wiſe man be of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that king <hi>Iohn</hi> coulde diſpoſe of the crowne of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> of himſelfe, without the aſſent and conſent of the ſtates, and ordaine forfeytures thereof to forreyners and ſtrangers. And although I can eaſily be perſwaded that the ſubiectes for the extreame hatred that they bare vnto their preſent prince,<note place="margin">The ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of the Canon</note> woulde lightly be wonne to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of cauſes to be diſcharged of their alleageanc to their king: yet can I hardly be induced to beleeue, that they coulde ſuffer themſelues, their wiues and children, landes and liuinges, goods and country to be expoſed to the ſacke and ſpoyle of all their neighbours, yea of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome if they ſhoulde vnhappily happe to haue a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked king. And alſo well might they ſatisfie the will and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the counſell, without any ſuch pernicious perill of there whole ſtate, and alſo retaine ſtill their ancient honour and liberty, if they themſelues did make choiſe of the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſhould purge them, (if that the law of God had not vtterly forbidden the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to rebell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their prince, were he neuer ſo wicked) and not fooliſhly bind themſelues to take a purga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of they know not whom, &amp; perhaps, vnhappily of ſuch
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2432:41"/> a one, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te likely to purge them of ill humors ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely, that he would deſtroy the habit of their bodye, And hereof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſaide an example they neded not to ſeeke far: For as the very ſame inſtant they had a very plaine proofe thereof in France, where the earle of <hi>Tolowſe</hi> was depriued of his earledome, becauſe he would not purge his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Albigenſes; and the earledome giuen by the Pope vnto <hi>Simon</hi> the Earle of <hi>Monſſort;</hi> For that I may omit how bloudily <hi>Monſſort</hi> executed the Popes mandate being ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the Croyſy againſt the Albigenſes in ſacking the Cities, murdering the men and women, how he did alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that pretence aſſaulte &amp; ſacke cityes, that were not one whit infected with that ſect, and ſlew in one battell twentie thouſand of the people, and their Alies; After he was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated earle by the Pope and counſell, and inueſted therein by the French King, and al the whole country had embraced him for their prince, he cruelly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded the citizens of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſane Towloſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Narbon</hi> to diſmantell their walles &amp; to fill vp their ditches. This to doe (ſaith <hi>Paulus Aemilius</hi> mine author alſo in the reſt of this hiſtory) they thought to be a wretched <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e pitifull thing, yet they executed his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the head of <hi>Simon,</hi> they begin with their owne hands to make their country naked of hir wals, they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues making the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſubiect vnto all iniury, Nether did that ſeme to be the greateſt of their euils, for <hi>Simon,</hi> both becauſe his purſe was well emptied through the charges of the warres, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo then he might throughly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame them being afflicted with miſeries, and manyfould miſchiefes, ſendeth about collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors and coactors to leuie a mightie maſſe of money of the country: It is ſtrange that nature hath ſo ordained that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans priuate damages doe moue him more then the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke ſorrowe, neyther can their be any ſharper weapon found then that of money. They which at his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ouerthrew their country, could not endure the loſſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2432:42"/> of their purſe. So that the warre that was ſaide &amp; p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to haue bene taken in hand, &amp; kept for godes cauſe; and might haue bene ended by ſparing of them that had yelde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and by deſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling of things paſt, was made now more hard to be ended through vnmercifull dealing. Dores were bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, open diſtreſſes were taken, ſighing, ſhriking, ſorrowing, weping &amp; wailing of men &amp; women, were harde in euery houſe. At length ſorrow being turned into anger, the olde Earle being then in hope of alteration, had returned out of Spaine whither he fled after his diſcomfiture in battell, was receiued of the Cyty of <hi>Tolouſe</hi> and other Cyties there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boutes, the byſhoppes whom Simon had reſtored were dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out againe, becauſe the multitude thought them to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour him. Then Aemilius ſeemeth to exclame againſt the wickedneſſe of this Canon, in giuing principalities to ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and ſheweth how hurtfull it is to gods cauſe, for the aduancement whereof it is ſuppoſed to be made thus ſaying, <hi>Nihil in ſacris bellis perinde obfuit, atque mos iam exortus, vt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſta proſcriptione ſuas quiſque reſpiciat res; in ore omnium ſanctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> piumque verſetur, conſilio; conatu, animo ſecus afficiantur. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de religione tantum agaetur, ſi obliuio noxae ſanciatur, ſi ſanatis mentibus fortunis hominum abſtineatur, omnes idem ſentiant, nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c de mortalium iure, de comitatures eſt, ea controuerſia tollatur, nulla erit armorum cauſa &amp;c.</hi> Nothing hath done ſo much hurt in the ſacred warres as a cuſtome that is now come vp, that euery man doth by honeſt preſcription regard and reſpect his owne, that in all their mouthes is hearde, holy and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but in drift, doings, and in hearte, they are otherwiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. If the matter be onely for religion, if it be decreed that the fault be forgotten and forgiuen, if when mens harts are healed their goodes be abſtained from, let them be all of one minde; Now the matter in hande is about the right of men, and about an Earledome, let that contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſy be taken away, and there is no cauſe of warres.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2432:42"/> 
               <hi>Ramond</hi> requeſteth his auncient patrimony, <hi>Simon</hi> holdeth faſt that, which he hath gotten by Armes, the gifte of the counſell, the benefite of the king of France. Theſe men are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill onely of there owne; But the Pope, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the matter had once before beene adiudged, doth thinke it to ſtande with his conſtancie, and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to haue, the ordinances of their fathers to abide ſtable, and his owne decrees inuiolable &amp;c. Thus the wiſe Barrons ſaw, and wee alſo may, that the warres in the Earledome of <hi>Towloſe</hi> had ceaſed when the cauſe ceaſed, that is, when the Albigenſes were expelled, and the Catholickes Romaine reſtored, if it had not bene for this decree of the Counſell that had adiudged the Earledome vnto <hi>Monſſort,</hi> which now, ſeeing they were not contented with the reformation of the Earledome, and the Earle, continued manie yeares after, almoſt to the vtter deſtruction of the Country, and alſo the death of <hi>Simon,</hi> who eight yeares after was in that quarrell, ſlaine at the ſeige of <hi>Tolowſe.</hi> But there ſonnes <hi>Almericke</hi> and <hi>Ramond</hi> continued theyr fathers contention. When <hi>Almericke</hi> findeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to weake, did three yeares after make ouer his right vnto <hi>Lewis</hi> the eight, the French King; for to bee created Conſtable of France, <hi>Lewes</hi> wanne <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninion</hi> by aſſault, yet dyed before hee could accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh his conqueſt: and his widdowe, and regent of his young ſonne followed the quarrell, and at length ended it, by compoſition, that Alphonſe hir younger ſonne ſhould marry with the ſole doughter and heyre of the Earle and enioy his earledome after his diſeaſe: this happened, <hi>Anno 1235,</hi> nyneteene yeares after that all warres for religion had ended. Soe greate a good had the firſt execution of this Canon wrought, I haue
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2432:43"/> dwelt the longer in the narration of this hiſtory, for to ſhew the inconuenience of this Canon, and alſo to ſet before the eyes of my Catholicke Countrimen, what curtſie they and theirs are like to finde at the handes of a forreyne Catholike. Prince, if any ſhould vnhappely (which God of his vnmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable mercy forbidde, and my hande ſhaketh to write) through their wicked and pernicious treaſon obtaine the conqueſt of this kingdome. But the engliſh nobilitie that liued at the counſell at <hi>Latarane</hi> could not forget the wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched wracke and waſt that a conqueſt bringeth, and the ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, miſery, and the extremity and curſed calamities, that the accepting of a forreine prince inferreth and enforceth, who then kept wofull warres, receiued from their aunceſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by many diſcents, for their auncient lawes and liberties, of whom they had beene cruelly ſpoyled by the conqerour &amp; his ſucceſſors, and alſo deliuered them vnto their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys almoſt to the deſtruction of the bloud Royall, well neere to the vtter ruine of their owne howſes, and the lamentable ſhipwracke of their deare country. Yea and what regard the nobilitie and people of this Land had then of any decree and Canon made by the Pope touching any temporall matter, it doth planely appeare by <hi>Mathew</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> who writeth that when the Pope had ſent Bulles of diſcharge of the Kinges oth, and graunt of their auncient lawes and liberties, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo excommunication againſt the Barrons, and their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents that did atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt to force King Iohn to the performance of them, The Barons would not obey them, but all men ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, and as it were with one mouth ſaide, that the Bulles were of no moment becauſe the ordering of laye matters did not appertaine vnto the Pope. For that onely the power to diſpoſe of Church matters was giuen by our Lord vnto <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and his ſucceſſors. What meanes the inſatiable coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe of the Romaines to ſtretch out it ſelfe vnto vs? what haue Apoſtolicke Byſhoppes to doe with warres?
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2432:43"/> See they will be the ſucceſſors of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and not of <hi>Peter</hi> &amp;c. And in this minde they continued in the reigne of king <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, when the Parliament aſſembled at <hi>Lincolne</hi> thus wrote (as we reade in <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>VValſingham</hi> &amp; <hi>flores hiſtoriarum</hi>) vnto <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the viii. who among other things in his letters to the king, had requeſted, that if the King had any right in the kingdomes of Scotland, or any part thereof, that he would ſend his proctors and learned counſell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and there the matter ſhoulde ſpeedily with iuſtice be adiudged &amp; decided. Neither that the kings of England had, by reaſon of the preeminence of their ſtate regall, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and coſtome at all times inuiolably obſerued, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer anſwered, or ought to anſwere before any Iudge eccele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall or ſecular about his rights in the aforeſaide king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Scotland, or other his temporalities: wherefore we hauing held a diligent conſultation &amp; deliberation vppon the contents of your aboueſaide letters, it was the common concordious, &amp; one minded conſent of vs all, &amp; of eueryone of vs, &amp; ſhalbe for euer hereafter vnaltered, that our foreſaid Lord the King doe not about the rights of the kingdome of Scotland, or other his temporalities in any wiſe, anſwere iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially before you, nor come vnder iudgement in any ſort, or bring his rights aforeſaide in doubt or queſtion, nor there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſende proctours or meſſengers vnto your preſence, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the premiſes doe tende manifeſtly to the diſinheriting of the right of the Crowne of the kingdome of England, and the kingly dignitie, &amp; the notorious ſubuerſion of the ſtate of the ſame kingdome; &amp; alſo to the preiudice of our fathers libertie, coſtoms, &amp; lawes, to the obſeruation and defending of whom, we are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by the duty of oth taken, &amp; the which we will maintaine in all that we can, and will with the helpe of God defend with all our ſtrength: Neither alſo doe wee permit, or in any ſort will ſuffer, as neither we can, nor ought, that our foreſaide Lord &amp; king, (yea if he would) doe, or in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2432:44"/> any cauſe attempt, the premiſes ſo vnwonted, vndue, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall, and at other times ſo vnheard of &amp;c. And now I pray you will any indifferent man beleeue, that our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen in thoſe daies did thinke, that the Pope had autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to deſpoſe their Kings, or knew or heard, that their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and aunceſtours had giuen the Pope power to expoſe the kingdome of their countrie, for a common pray for all Chriſtians and Catholickes; But now hauing prooued that this Canon cannot bind vs now, vnleſſe our anceſtours had receaued by conſent of Parliament, &amp; alſo haue ſhewed that it neither was, nor could be done; let vs fall to our ſeconde proofe that the Canons of this Counſell at leaſt in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall caſes, were neuer receiued in this Realme. In this counſel there was a Canon made vnder payne of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication, that the Clergy ſhould not be forced to pay any contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſecular princes, neither ſhoulde they willingly of their owne accord pay any, without licence firſt obtained of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Pope: Now that this Canon was neuer in force here, it doth plainely appeare by the ſubſidies payde by the Clergy vnto the ſonne of King <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Henry</hi> the third, in the ix. the xvi the xxi. the xxix. the xxxvii. the xliiii. the xlii. yeares of his raigne, neuer once aſked the Popes conſent, but contrariwiſe in the xxxvi. yeares of his raigne the king hauing the popes mandate from the Counſell of <hi>Lyons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hed.</note> to pay him three ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes becauſe he was croſſed for the holy land, they vtterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to pay him penny. The Clergy did alſo wthout contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction pay vnto his ſonne and ſucceſſor <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt in the eight yeare of his reaigne thre tenthes, and in the elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth yeare the twentith part of all their goodes, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward at the Parliament helde at Saint <hi>Edmondeſbury, Robert</hi> the Archbyſhoppe of Canterbury and ſome of the Clergy refuſed to pay, not claming to be exempted by this Canon but by another decre made lately that very yeare by Pope
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2432:44"/> 
               <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the eight, but then the King put the Cleargy out of his protection; and thus forced them to yeelde, and ſo they haue continued payment quietly euer ſince that time; An other Canon we haue in the ſame counſell, <hi>Chap. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> that no preſcription ſhall be good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the whole time whereof the poſſeſſor did not verelye beleeue that the thing was his owne in truth, But that the law of this land did neuer make any diſtinction of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion <hi>bona</hi> or <hi>malae fidei,</hi> whether the poſſeſſor did think it to be his owne or not at all, our Lawyers doe know and acknowledge. And alſo the ſtatutes of limitation made in the Parliamentes held at <hi>Marton</hi> and <hi>VVest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> in the three and twentie yeares of the raignes of <hi>Henry</hi> the third and <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt doe plainelie prooue. Alſo a third Canon there is, a branch of this of the deſpoſition of Princes, that the goodes of Clar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes condemned for heretikes ſhall bee forfeited vnto the Churches where they ſerued.</p>
            <p>This conſtitution not to bee obſerued, the author of the booke called the Doctor and the Student doth at large prooue in the xxix. Chapter of his ſeconde booke, And alſo it doth plainely appeare by the ſtatute made in the ſecond yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt <hi>Chapt. 7.</hi> where wee finde that the goodes of Heretikes of what eſtate, condition and degree ſoeuer they bee, are eſcheated to the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And alſo all their landes that houlde imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately of him, or of their ordinaries or their commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: but the landes of all other that holde in chiefe of other Lordes, the king to haue them a yeare and a day with their waſtes, and afterward to returne vnto the Lord of the ſea. And ſeeing that in three ſmall matters that touched not the ſtate, the Counſell was not, nor is receiued, can anye wiſe man beleeue that the Counſell was receaued in
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2432:45"/> a Canon that touched the ruine of the whole country and kingdome, and namely, ſeeing it hath beene plainely proued, that a part of the very ſelfe ſame Canon was neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
            <p>Now finally to conclude: neither was the ſentence of depriuation canonically pronounced againſt her Maieſtie, according to thee decree of the Counſell,<note place="margin">The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non not orderly executed.</note> for whereas ſhe ſhould firſt haue bene admoniſhed by the Church, and then excommunicated by the Metropolitane, and his compro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciall Byſhoppes; and then if ſhe had contemned to ſatiſfie within one yeare, to bee depriued, &amp;c. It is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that ſhe was not excommunicated by the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politane, and the Byſhoppes of his prouince, neyther I doe thinke admoniſhed by the Church, but euen at the very firſt choppe depoſed by the Pope. Therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that neyther Pope, nor generall counſell haue autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to depoſe Princes, or releaſe ſubiectes of their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, neyther was the Canon of the Counſell of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane</hi> for depoſing of Princes euer receiued in this land, nor any other Canons of Counſels that touched tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralities, neyther yet that Canon orderly executed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-againſt her Maieſty. What good Chriſtian Engliſh man can thinke, that hee was by that Bull of <hi>Pius Quin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> diſcharged of his obedience, and allegiance that hee oweth vnto her Maieſtye: And can abſurdly beleeue, that all thoſe that ſhall dye in that quarell ſhall vndoubtedlye bee damned in hell fire, with all miſcreants and rebelles.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2432:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
